They are like a pig.
Thank you.
Okay.
The second thing is that I will make it easier to take.
When I use this, I will make a little more.
I will make a couple of minutes.
I will make a lot of time.
so
Let me just wait one more minute and then we'll start to the manager.
Yeah, I'll be right back.
Okay.
You can cut the
the
one and then
one.
I'm going to
get a little
more
longer.
I'm going to
do
a little
more
than
you
can
Let's go.
I will use the
Thank you.
All the parts we come out.
Okay, let's go ahead and start the lecture.
Welcome back to distributed systems one.
Let's start with announcements first and then we'll do a Q&A.
Okay, and then what I want to do tonight is I want to talk about programming assignment
two.
So we'll spend the better part of the first lecture
talking about Programming Assignment 2.
I know you still have, right,
some time to work on Programming Assignment 1.
So it's due next week on Tuesday.
But I want to introduce it because of the extension,
they're going to overlap by a week, okay?
But anyways, you can always come back to the lecture
and go over what we discussed about Programming Assignment 2.
Then we'll start talking about architectures
in distributed systems closer to the second half
for during the second half of the lecture.
So in terms of announcements, programming assignment one is due next week on Tuesday
at midnight.
I did receive some emails from students regarding accessing their account.
So if you haven't had the chance to access your account yet for programming assignment
one, please go ahead and try.
If it says that your account is deactivated, send me an email so I can reactivate your
account.
I think you have only a few days after I activate the account to go ahead and access your account and set up your password and two-factor authentication before it gets deactivated.
Okay?
So please make sure that you do that ahead of time.
I'll be available during the week.
So during the work days, I'll be able to answer the same day or if you send the email.
You know at night, I'll answer the next morning, you know, but during the weekends my time might be a little bit more sparse
So you know try not to leave the account activation for the weekend, okay?
Then quiz number two has been posted as well
So you have until next week on Monday to complete the quiz
It will cover the entirety of chapter one, so you'll probably
See some questions from quiz one as well
Yes, will you release like the solution for quiz one because like I wasn't able to see
see which ones I got wrong?
Yeah, so the solutions get automatically
released on Wednesday
morning at
sort of after midnight.
So after midnight on Tuesday,
going into Wednesday, you'll be able
to see the results. They don't get released
immediately after the deadline.
So maybe if you want during the break
I can go together on your computer
and we can try to see, but you should be able to see
the questions and the answers.
but they get released two days after the deadline.
And then the last part is that Programming Assignment 2 has been released
and you have until Tuesday, October 6th to complete Programming Assignment 2
so you have two weeks to complete this assignment.
Well, before that, any questions regarding Programming Assignment 1
the quizzes, class contents, I'd be more than happy to answer.
Okay. Yes?
Do the quizzes also contribute towards the grade at the end of the term?
Correct, correct. So yeah, each quiz
is worth 2.5 percent of the final grade, and then you also
have an extra credit quiz that is also worth 2.5 percent.
So you can get a maximum of 20 percent from the quizzes.
So they do contribute to 20 percent of the final grade.
I haven't been able to attempt the quiz one.
Unfortunately like the syllabuses, no make up, you cannot take them later, so you have
to make sure you take them on time.
You will be able to take the extractor quiz which will allow you to regain the last points.
Okay, so make sure that again you take the quizzes on time.
They get released every Wednesday and you have until the next Monday to complete them.
Okay, any other questions?
Alright, if there are no other questions
then as I said what I want to do is I want to talk today about Programming Assignment 2
What I'll do is I'll
explain the application that you have to implement plus a lot of the details
of the assignment. So as similar to
Programming Assignment 1, you can get 100 points on this assignment
This is an individual assignment of course and then
similar to programming assignment 1 you will need to submit your report to D2L and then the code to
your GitLab repository so for this assignment there's a new GitLab repository that got created
for you on the neutron server so for each assignment you have a unique repository
compared to programming assignment 1 this actually this assignment actually comes with skeleton code
okay so you have some starting code and read me as well and instructions that
you need to follow in your GitLab repository so please make sure that
after you're done with programming assignment one go and check to see that
you can access your GitLab repository for programming assignment two to make
sure that everything is fine also compared to programming assignment one
so in programming assignment one you needed to do some setup to set up your
programming environment. This is the only assignment where you need to install things,
set up things. Starting with programming assignment, we would be using that environment to implement
code. So the rest of the assignments will be more programming focused. Now, what this assignment
asks you to do, it asks you to implement a Fire Retrieval Engine application. So an
information retrieval engine application is an application that tries to solve
the following problem. It tries to implement a system
that allows a user to retrieve
a subset of documents from a collection of documents
in order to satisfy an information need. Now I said I used the term
collection of documents but they don't have to be documents. For example, when we go
and use Google search or DuckDuckGo over the internet
what the search engine does, it retrieves a subset of web pages that satisfies the information need.
We usually express that information need through some sort of search query.
So I know that I think nowadays we're all using the AI tools like Gemini,
ChGBT, Cloud to get answers, right?
But before those tools we used to use Google search and Tuck that goal more out
to, again, retrieve information.
So you need to implement a similar application.
Now, I know when it comes to web data,
this problem has been solved by Google, and Microsoft, and DuckDuckGo.
However, when we talk about search engines,
search engines exist not only for web data.
They also exist for your local data that is stored on your computer.
So most operating systems become pre-installed
some sort of file retrieval search engine.
So Windows has a search engine built in, Mac OS in the Finder, you can search for documents on your computer, and then various Linux distributions they implemented using various kinds of applications.
so what you will need to implement
in this assignment is you will need to implement
your own application
that does file retrieval
so basically this
application
you see there's arguments
a folder path
and you will need to go over that folder path
reorganize the data in a way
we'll introduce the notion of the index very shortly
which an index is a way to reorganize
the data and then we'll need to
allow the user to do search operations
over that index or over that data reorganization.
If I were to ask you, you know, like, hey, if, you know, you have, let's say, a computer
and you have one terabyte of data there in a folder, right, and if I were to ask you,
can you, you know, write a program that, you know, scans, you know, the entire, you know,
one terabyte of data and returns all of the documents that contains, let's say,
cats and dogs so all the documents that talk about cats and dogs you know how would you write that
program what would be some of the you know let's say basic steps that you would need to do in the
program in order to be able to find all of those documents yes read the files in the folder so
we read the files right but let's say that you know i give you a folder that might have other
subfolders that have other subfolders and so on and so forth.
So what would you need to do to identify all of the files?
Like recursively look at everything?
Exactly.
Recursively traverse, let's say, the file system hierarchy.
So modern day file systems on computers, they are organized in a hierarchical fashion.
So which means they kind of look like a tree.
You have a starting point and then you can traverse the tree.
What's interesting, the property of this hierarchy is that the leaf nodes represent the actual files.
The intermediary nodes, they represent the folders in your system.
So you'll need to traverse the entire folder, extract all of the file paths.
So then what follows afterwards if you wanted to identify those documents?
If it's a binary file, I'd probably ignore it.
Exactly.
If it's a binary file, I'd ignore it.
So if it's human readable, if it's a TXT, a PDF, or a doc, that's when you would go ahead and read the data from the file.
And then you read the data, and what you will do is you will try to extract the words or the tokens from each file
and see if they match with the keywords that were passed as a search query.
See if they match with cats or dogs.
Very simple.
Again, anyone can write this program.
It's not very complicated.
But the question is, is this program the best program to write for this kind of problem?
So let's say, again, you have 1 terabyte of data on your computer, right?
And let's say that that 1 terabyte of data is stored on a SATA SSD.
So as we mentioned before, you know, a SATA SSD, you can read the data from the SATA SSD at about 500 megabytes per second.
550, give or take, okay?
But let's say 500 megabytes per second, right?
And so the question is, for one search query, how much time would this program take to actually
give you the results?
Right, if you have one terabyte of data, 500 megabytes per second, how many seconds will
it take to actually get a result?
Yeah, so one terabyte is 1000 gigabytes, yeah.
At worst, it's two seconds.
Or even more, right?
So one terabyte of data is, you know, 1,000 gigabytes, right?
And you can read at 500 megabytes per second.
It's like half a gigabyte, right?
So it would take you about 2,000, right, seconds to actually get the result.
I know if we use the search engine, the search engine gives it very fast, right?
In about, well, like you said, in about two seconds, you get the result, right?
But this program, right, is not very efficient because it needs to scan those documents every single time you want to search for it.
So that's why what we want to do is we want to build an index or some sort of search engine that actually reorganizes the data so that we can have an easier time searching for it.
Okay, so we'll explore what that means.
Now, one very important property, and you will see this in the overview of this assignment, is this application that you need to write needs to follow a specific architecture structure.
This is called the application layering architecture.
I will describe what this means in the context of this assignment by now, and then in the second half of the lecture, once we start talking about architectures and distributed systems, we'll see where this application layering fits, okay?
But for now, just know that your application has to follow this application layering architecture.
Some other properties of your application.
It needs to support two types of operations.
So this application, and maybe a little bit of a parenthesis before I talk about those two operations.
So for the rest of the quarter, you will be working on the exact same application.
So you'll be implementing a file retrieval engine.
But we'll try, as the quarter progresses, we'll try to make this application more and more distributed.
But first, we start with a monolithic application.
application. Monolithic means one single process, one single thread, one single user. Okay, very
simple. We focus more on the logic of the application and how to implement its functionality.
In programming assignment 3, I will ask you to actually try to improve the performance of the
application by using multi-threading. In programming assignment 4, we'll make it, you know,
client server so you can have multiple users connect to the application simultaneously,
and then we'll explore various kinds of communication technologies.
So going back to this application, the application needs to support two kinds of operation
to its user for now and users in the future.
So it needs to support an index operation.
The index operation basically tells the program that, hey, read all of the contents from a
folder.
So identify all of the files in the folder, you know, in the subfolders as well, read
their contents and reorganize them in a way where I can do search operations.
And then the second kind of operation that a user can do is search operations.
So the user can run a search query to retrieve the documents that are relevant for the query.
Now, when I mention, you know, the application, the simple application that basically does a scanning of all of the documents to identify all of the documents that contains cats and dogs,
what we did, actually, we only did data retrieval.
We didn't do information retrieval.
Mother-day search engines, they do information retrieval.
retrieval? Data retrieval
means that I returned all
of the data
in a way
where I do not capture
any kind of
information or relevance
about the document. So I returned
the document in a
insignificant order.
Now,
when you go and use a search engine on Google,
it tries to return you
the most relevant pages. The pages
that are relevant for the query.
The way search engines determine relevance, they use different kinds of mathematical models.
For this assignment and the rest of the assignments, we will be using a very simple model to determine relevance
because we want to return the top 10 documents whenever we do a search,
kind of like Google does when it returns the top 10 pages or web pages.
So the way we will encode relevance is through the notion of word frequency.
So let's say, for example, that I identify a thousand documents that contains dogs and cats, right?
I will consider that the document that has the most amount of occurrences of both cats and dogs,
so both of these words, I would consider them to be the most important document, right?
So let's say if I have a document that contains cats and dogs a thousand times,
and then I have another document that contains cats and dogs combined only ten times,
I would say that the document that has 1,000 occurrences of these words is more important, more relevant than the document that has least amount of occurrence.
In reality, people use more sophisticated models to compute relevance.
If you're interested in learning more about those models, just let me know.
Some of the models that you can find out there that are very popular and are used in enterprise search systems like Apache Lucene, Apache Solar Elasticsearch, OpenSearch, are TFIDF.
It stands for Term Frequency Inverse Document Frequency, and then BM25, which also does a normalization.
Anyways, for this assignment, you only have to count frequencies in order to return the most relevant documents.
Okay, so when it comes to the search query, the most simple search engine will accept only one word as a search, let's say, operator.
However, I'd like you in this assignment for your application to be able to support multi-term queries.
So you're able to pass multiple words or multiple keywords or tokens when you do a search operation, kind of like what Google does.
Now, for the purpose of this assignment, your application is to support a maximum of three words and a minimum of one word.
So you can do one term, two term, or three term queries.
We'll see what the difference between them are.
Now, when we encode multi-term queries, in literature, there are various ways you can encode or determine how do you combine these terms.
For the purpose of this assignment, we will be using the AND operation, so we want to say that we're doing AND queries.
This means that I want to return all of the documents that contains at least one instance of each of the terms from my query.
So if I'm searching for cats and dogs and tigers, I want to return only the documents that contains at least one instance of cats, one instance of dogs, and one instance of tigers in the documents.
If a document only contains cats and tigers and doesn't contain dogs, then I do not return it as a result.
Okay, this is akin to doing an intersection operation between the documents returned by each term.
We will see this, we'll come back to it.
So, again, whenever you do a search operation, your program needs to return the top 10 most relevant documents.
So the document that contains all of the terms from the query and sorted by cumulative frequency.
So cumulative means that I'm adding all of the frequency of all of the words when I create that relevance for each document.
Now, when it comes to the programming languages that you are allowed to use for this assignment,
You may use C++ or Java or Go or Rust.
I have a skeleton code for each of these programming languages, okay,
and you're allowed to use the standard library for these languages.
You only have to use one of these languages.
So if you want to implement all of them for fun, go ahead and do it.
Okay, you're not going to gain any extra points, but you might gain extra experience.
All right.
When it comes to the development and evaluation of this assignment,
You will need to do it on a Ubuntu 2604 LTS Server Edition machine.
You already have that virtual machine set up for programming assignment 1,
so feel free to use it.
And feel free, once you transition to Programming Assignment 2,
to increase the amount of RAM and increase the amount of cores
your virtual machine has.
You might need it, actually.
It might make it a little bit easier when you write the program
because you won't have to write it in a way where you use least amount of them.
as long as your computer can support it, of course.
So, don't go over the layers.
The grader will also use the same environment
to grade your assignment.
There's also an automated grading script as well
that will be used.
And then, as part of this assignment,
in addition to writing the code,
so implementing the application,
you will also need to do a performance evaluation.
So, since this is a distributed systems class,
and we know that one of the design goals of distributed systems
is size scalability, so how do we make the application run well?
I'd like you to actually do a similar analysis for this application.
So what I'd like you to analyze is how does the performance
of your application change with increasing data set size?
And for that, I provided you with three data sets.
I'll talk about them a little bit later.
And I'll talk about what performance evaluation means as well.
Now, if at any point you have any questions regarding the assignment, just feel free to interrupt.
I'd be more than happy to answer the questions.
Now, when it comes to the architecture of this application,
figure 1 from the assignment description describes this application layering architecture that their application has to follow.
The application layering, it's a very simple architecture.
It's a layered architecture.
So it basically creates a bunch of components that are organized in a layered fashion.
The layer on the top is the layer that the user interacts with.
And then the layer on the top usually relies on a layer below to provide different kinds of services.
And the layer below relies on another layer that sits another level below the current layer.
Okay.
So in the case of the application layering architecture, there exists three layers.
and each layer has a specific responsibility.
And most computer science applications can be organized in these three layers.
Okay?
So let's start with the first layer on the top.
This is the layer that the user will interact with.
This is typically called the application interface layer.
So your program needs to have a layer that encodes the logic of implementing the application interface.
Now, the application interface can be implemented in various ways.
You can have a graphical user interface.
You can have a web-based interface.
You can have a command-line-based interface.
For this assignment, you only need to implement a command-line-based interface.
So, command-line-based means you start a program from the command line.
The program will print a prompt.
Once it's loaded, it will ask the user, hey, give me a command.
And there will be three commands that you will need to implement the details with you.
So, once the user punches in a command, right,
And the commands, they will be equivalent to the kind of operations that the user can do on your application.
So there will be an index command and then a search command that you pass.
So the application interface is only responsible with processing the command, the arguments of the command,
and then calling a method from the layer below in order to implement the actual logic of the operation.
So this takes us to the processing engine layer.
The processing engine, or the processing layer, is responsible with implementing the actual logic of your application.
In this case, it provides two methods to the layer above.
It provides a search and an index folder method, equivalent to the two operations that the user can do.
The processing engine is then responsible with actually implementing the indexing process,
and we'll talk about it in the first half of the lecture
and also for the search operations as well.
Now, the processing engine is always possible with the computational aspects.
Since you are implementing a search engine,
you will need to operate on an index data structure,
that reorganization of the data.
And this refers now to the data aspect of an application.
So in an application layering architecture,
we have a third layer that usually sits at the bottom.
This layer is typically called the data layer and is the layer responsible with storing the data.
Now, the way you would be storing the data in this application is, of course, in a non-persistent fashion.
So, you're storing the data, the index in memory.
This means that if you shut down your program and start it again,
then the program will forget everything about the index that it uses.
And this is done by design so we can do performance evaluations.
All right.
So, the data layer in this application is called the index store.
So this is the layer responsible with actually storing the index
and for providing look-up operations over the index.
You will see by index, we mean actually two components there.
We mean a document map and a term of inverter data.
So we will explain all these.
Okay, but the processing engine, once it's done computing,
either the indexing operation or the search operation,
we will contact the index store during the operation
or once the operation is completed.
Once an operation is completed by the processing engine,
the processing engine will return to the application interface,
and the application interface can print some sort of useful message for the user.
It's not actually some sort.
You have to print a specific kind of message.
This is included in the skeleton code, in the Read Me part of the skeleton code.
You know, it includes the details that you have to print
so that the autocrater can detect them as well.
Okay?
But basically, for both operations,
the application interface needs to print the total amount of bytes
that were processed during the index process
and how much time it took to do indexing
and then for the search operations
and how much time it took to do a search operation
but also the results as well sorted by
of course by the relevance score, by the frequency.
Okay.
So you'll be able to find for each of these components
you'll be able to find detailed descriptions
in the assignment
and I encourage you to go ahead and read them
and then to take notes or to highlight
you know, the parts that are important.
What I did is I also provided, using bold text,
some more important parts, the details of the application.
So when it comes to search engines,
one decision that the software engineers
that build search engines, that they have to make,
is they have to decide what is the vocabulary
of the search engine that they want to build.
So what do we consider to be a token,
and what do we consider to be a delimiter,
or what do we consider to be a word and what do we consider to be a space between words?
So in the context of this assignment, there's a specific definition of what a valid word is.
We define this right here in bold.
We say that a word is a contiguous sequence that has alphanumeric characters
and or hyphen and or underscore characters.
Okay, so any kind of character that is not alphanumeric, that is not hyphen and not underscore, is considered to be a delimiter.
Also, in this assignment, I am asking you to implement a search engine that is actually case sensitive.
Now, in practice, when people build actual search engines, the search engine is case insensitive.
So when they look at the words, for example, from the English language, they will do a lowercase on all of the words.
They also do additional transformations that we don't do in this assignment.
We do stemming, we break down words into the root form, but we don't do that.
I want you to experience what it's like to index data that actually cannot be broken down into root form.
And this is very typical, for example, for scientific data.
I know maybe I mentioned, I think in the lecture recording in the first lecture, the kind of work that I do.
So I work at the intersection of distributed systems and information retrieval.
So this homework assignment is a small taste of the kind of work that I do.
And again, like I said, when it comes to doing search over web data, this has been solved.
When it comes to doing search over enterprise data, we have a lot of solutions out there.
But when it comes to doing search over scientific data, we don't really have a lot of good tools to do that by now.
So for web data, it's very interesting, the data has a few properties.
In web data, there's a lot of text out there, right?
When people build the internet, there was a lot of text before they had audio and video and image data.
And even if a web page does have audio, video, or image data, a lot of the times that kind of multimodal data is surrounded by text data.
So Google can use clever algorithms to infer that, oh, this image talks about whatever the content of the text around it is.
So they can build clever indexes.
In the enterprise world, the data that they have is typically structured or semi-structured.
So enterprise, I mean companies, they have databases.
Those are typically structured.
We have tables that are related to other tables.
Semi-structured, you know, you maybe have reports, forms, right?
So you can extract that data in a semi-structured way.
Now, when it comes to science, there is no general scientific data format.
So each scientific community has their own ways of representing data.
In, let's say, medicine, they have specific formats for representing, for example, CT scans data.
Even though we look at one image, in reality, the data that they work with is actually very sophisticated.
It has a lot of details about how the CT scan was done,
and when they do a CT scan, they do actually a volume, let's say, scan of your body,
and then they only take a picture of one of the segments there.
But there's multiple segments.
And in reality, when we store that data on the computer,
we don't really store the segment information.
We store a bunch of information, and then we use a program
to actually draw the different segments of the CT scan.
and I can numerate a lot of other scientific domains.
So what's interesting about their data sets
is that they contain a lot of alphanumeric characters.
So that's why in this assignment,
I'd like you to, again, consider that your tokens
or your words or vocabulary is actually composed
out of alphanumeric underscore and hyphen character sequences.
And then the last characteristic is that
if you have a continuous sequence of alphanumeric underscore
and hyphen characters, they are considered to be a word only
and only if the length of that sequence is greater than
3. This will allow you to have an index
that will not explode in memory, okay, and will allow you to avoid certain
kind of stop words, okay? So let me give you some examples
of what qualifies as
good examples of
words and what does not qualify
as good examples of words.
Alright, so let's start with
let's say uppercase cat
let's also include
dogs with lower d
dogs. Let's also include moonlight. And then let's also include, let's say, document11-csc.txt.
Alright, so the first word here, this does not qualify as a valid word for your search engine for this application because it has a length of 3.
So only the words that have a length greater than 3 qualify as a word.
So this will not be indexed, and when you do a search, you should ignore this term.
Dogs does qualify because it has a length of 4, it's made of alphanumatic, all great.
Now, dogs with lowercase d also qualifies, but it's different from the dogs with uppercase d because the application is case sensitive.
Okay.
Now, if you have moon dash light, so the hyphen here, right, this is also a valid character inside a word.
So moonlight would be treated as one single word.
You don't have to split moon and light.
I know a real search engine would split probably or would index all of them together.
Okay, but we don't have to do those kinds of complicated operations in this assignment.
And then lastly, if we look at the example of document 11 underscore CSE dot TXT, right?
As we said, any kind of character that is not alphanumeric hyphen or underscore is a delimiter.
So this period here is a delimiter, right?
So we delimit these two different words.
Now, doc11 underscore CSE is considered as one single word, right?
It's alphanumeric.
It has both letters and digits.
Plus underscore is a valid character.
Okay?
But then, does TXT count as a valid word?
No.
Why does it not count as a valid word?
Too short.
Too short, right?
So, it's not long enough.
Perfect.
So, this does not qualify.
Okay?
So, that's how I'd like you to encode in the application what is a valid word and what
it's not a valid word.
Okay?
Both when you do indexing and also when you do search.
All right.
Very good.
Okay.
All right.
So then you have more details about the implementation of each of the layers, okay, each of the methods supported by the layers.
what I want to go now is I want to go
over the command line interface
specifications, right, so as any other application
it has some specifications on how
the user will interact with the application
as I mentioned, you have to
implement a command line interface and the
command line interface needs to implement three
commands, the first command is
the quit command which basically shuts
down the application in a graceful way
so basically if you have
memory that needs to be deallocated depending
on your programming language, right, if you choose
C++, and you manually
allocate memory, then at first you have to
deallocate the memory manually.
If you have Java or Go, you have
the garbage collector which will do that for you.
And then if you use Rust,
you can use the borrow
in mechanisms to have Rust
automatically deallocate the memory for you
at the end of your program.
Then the
other command that you need to implement is the
index command, which is equivalent to doing
the index operation. This index command
will receive one argument and that argument
It would be a folder path.
That, then your program will need to traverse,
identify all the files, index all of the files,
and then provide search services all.
And then the last command is the search command.
The search command can receive one or more arguments.
The arguments will represent the terms that are part of your AND query,
and they need to be separated by the AND keyword.
So, for example, I can search for only cats, and I do search cats.
if I want to search for cats and dogs, I will type in search cats and then uppercase N and then dogs.
Okay, and this will tell the system that you're doing a multi-term query.
Okay.
Any questions so far?
Yes.
There's a specific way you want us to handle if the search query has extra words like or or odd or something.
Now, for example, if somebody passes, you know, cats and or dogs or something, right?
So that would be an incorrect query because you have cats, the and keyword, which separates, you know, the different terms.
The second term would be or, which then would be ignored because it has a length, you know, of two, so it doesn't qualify as an actual term.
Right?
But then the next term would be dogs, which then would be incorrect because you should have the and keyword.
So basically when you have a three-term query, you do cats and dogs and tigers.
So just do nothing and ask for it.
Just do nothing, throw an error, it's incorrect.
I will not test that in the asylum.
So the autograder script will just run the queries, single-term queries and then multi-term queries separated by the and keyword.
Okay.
All right, very good.
So, as I mentioned, so it's not enough to just implement the application.
Of course, anyone can go and implement this application.
But what we care is, of course, we care about this becoming a distributed system throughout
this quarter.
And, of course, what we care about, one of the goals is size scalability.
So we care to see how well does our application work.
So what I did in order for you to be able to evaluate the performance of this application
I created three data sets.
The three data sets are derived from the Gutenberg Project data set.
The Gutenberg Project data set is a public data set that people can use
and it's typically used to evaluate information retrieval systems.
The data set is composed out of digital copies of books from the public domain.
So these are, again, books that are available for free.
They're already converted into a digital format for you.
They're converted into ASCII, so you don't have to deal with UTF-8.
What I did is I cleaned the data sets, and I organized them in an unbalanced way.
We'll see what this means once we look at the data sets themselves.
Then what you need to do as part of this assignment, of course, is you need to evaluate the performance.
Now, I just want to make a small parenthesis here.
when it comes to evaluating search engines.
If you ask people from the, let's say, sub-area
of computer science that studies information theory
and information systems, the way that they measure
the performance of search engines is from a quality perspective.
So they're interested to see how well does the search engine work
and does it return the most relevant data or not.
And for that, they use different kinds of metrics.
They use accuracy, recall, precision, you know, to see how well does the engine work.
Now, we don't care about that because we are in a distributed systems class.
So when I talk about performance here, what we want to analyze, we want to analyze the application from a systems perspective.
We're more interested in how fast things are processed.
So latency, how much time they take, or what is the processing speed measured in truth.
So for this assignment, what you need to do for the performance evaluation, you will need to run your application three times, once for each dataset.
Every single performance evaluation run, you will need to index the given dataset, and then you will need to provide some search queries.
And then you will need to measure the execution, the performance, the system's performance.
Now, the way you would be measuring the system's performance is by looking at indexing throughput.
So there are two ways, right?
You can measure to see for each given data set how much time did it take to build the index.
But what I'm more curious about is how does the performance change with increasing data set?
So I kind of want to see the speed of indexing.
So for that, we define indexing throughput as the total number of bytes that were indexed divided by the total amount of time.
And this will give you some sort of number that is measured in megabytes per second,
gigabytes per second, which will tell you how fast your system is running.
Once we change the dataset size, the expectation is that the processing speed should remain the same.
Even though the dataset changes and the amount of time changes,
the processing speed should be the same.
But you will see that the processing speed actually changes.
And we'll talk more about why that is the case once you're done with the programming design.
So this means that in your report, you need to include this performance evaluation, which means including a table with the results.
So for each data set, you include, you know, what is the indexing throughput that you measure.
And then you also need to answer five questions, okay?
All the assignments will have some sort of questions that you will need to answer, okay?
The questions are, you know, related to the data sets, to the implementation details, okay?
So, for example, in the first question, I'm asking, what is the difference between the wall time and the CPU time?
What method and function do you use to measure the wall time?
Now, out of curiosity, I'm not really sure, because we usually focus in the introductory courses.
We focus more on, you know, writing programs, on, you know, understanding data structures.
But I don't know if people really talk about performance.
Maybe in algorithms, we talk about time complexity,
to understand at an abstract level how many execution steps will the program take.
But when it comes to measuring the actual execution time,
because this is what an end user will see when I'm downloading the data from Google Drive,
I can see, oh, it takes 10 seconds, but it takes two seconds.
I can see it and notice it.
Has anyone heard of these notions of wall time and CPU time?
And if you did, do you know what's the difference between them?
Yes.
CPU time, the amount of time the CPU is actually doing operations for this,
not like reading in data or if it's waiting for something.
Yep. Very good. Very good.
And the whole time is the total time, including those wait times.
So another way to define this, right?
So CPU time is the amount of time that a process spends on the CPU, so it's active on the CPU.
Now we know that programs sometimes also read data from the disk, for example, or from the network.
And when they read that data, actually the process is they go to sleep and they wait until the data arrives in memory.
The kernel brings the data into memory.
So the CPU time does not take that time into account.
does not take the time that the process waits for data to come from disk or from network.
So this is useful for people who want to measure the performance of programs that stay on the CPU.
And they want to measure cycles, usually for low-level optimizations.
Now, for the end user and for distributed systems, what we care more about is the wall time.
The wall time is the CPU time plus the wait time.
It's the real time that it takes to actually run the application.
So, that's what I would like you to measure as well in your program.
So, you'll have to figure out, for each programming language, how do you actually measure the
whole time.
Okay, you'll be able to find on the internet, there's a lot of resources nowadays.
Okay?
But make sure that that's what you want to measure for this assignment, not the CPU
time.
All right, very good.
And this has to do, again, with distributed systems because, right, a lot of the time
distributed systems, they have to process large amounts of data.
So, it's important to understand, right, where are the stalls coming from?
Are they coming from reading, the data from a disk, from network, or does this all come from CPU or memory?
Another question, for example, it's asking you, you know, what are, what is the size of data set one and data set three, right, measured in both megabytes and maybe bytes, right?
They sound very similar, right, but they actually, there's a difference between them.
So, I'll let you search on the internet, you know, the difference between megabytes and maybe bytes.
And if you search some videos on the internet, they might tell you that hey this is how hard drive and SSD vendors try to trick you by using these terms interchangeably to sell you less storage for the same price.
So anyways, it's useful to understand.
What data structures do you use to implement an index store component?
We will see very shortly what kind of data structures you can use.
What is the difference between compute intensive, memory intensive, and I.O. intensive applications?
Now I know these are things that we haven't talked about in detail.
So the way you can think about compute-intensive, memory-intensive, and IO-intensive,
if you can remember the conversation that we had last week,
we talked about when it comes to size scalability,
some of the bottlenecks that can appear have to do with the components of the computer.
So we want to add more computers because, for example,
our application depends on the performance of the CPU,
right and we cannot buy a more powerful cpu so we add another computer with another powerful cpu
or maybe the application depends more on how fast the memory system is right so in for example we
can have applications that exhibit random memory access so they cannot benefit from the cpu cache
we cannot you know bring the data closer to the cpu so then we are at the mercy of how fast the
memory subsystem is or we might have application that process large amounts of data that cannot
it into memory, so we need to read and write data a lot, so this means that the performance
of the application depends on how fast we can read data from this, and if we can
keep it in memory in an additional way. So, for each of these
let's say components of a
computer, you can have an application that has
a bottleneck, that one of the components becomes a bottleneck for the application.
So we say that an application is compute intensive, if
the speed of the application depends on the CPU, on the speed of the CPU.
So, right, you implement an application, and even for this performance evaluation,
know that when you do this performance evaluation, you will get some numbers.
Your numbers will probably be very different from the numbers of one of your colleagues
because, right, the performance will depend on the software implementation,
but also on the hardware in which the software is running.
So even if you have the same software implementation,
if you have different hardware, you're going to get different performance.
But, again, if an application, if the performance of the application
depends on how fast the processor is running,
that would be computer-intensive application.
If an application depends on how fast the memory subsystem
can bring data to the CPU,
then it means it's a memory-intensive application.
Typically, applications that exhibit random memory access,
they are memory-intensive.
And then lastly, IO-intensive applications are applications that depend on the speed of the hard drive or of the network, so the input-output devices.
So this is usually applications that have large amounts of data that cannot fit into memory, usually become IO-intensive.
Now it depends. If you're just reading the data once and processing things, that's fine.
It's only when you have to do read and write.
So then, the last question that we have to answer
is, is the processing engine component
compute intensive, memory intensive, or IO intensive, and why?
This question is actually tied to the data structure
that I used to implement the index store.
This is the hint that I'm going to give you.
We can come back to this question next week as well.
So, once you're done with the code,
you perform the evaluation.
And then once you perform the evaluation, you're ready to submit your assignment.
Again, you'll be submitting the assignment on neutron.cdm.depon.edu using Git commands, just like in programming assignment one.
I'm going to remind you again, you're going to have a separate repository for this assignment.
If for some reason you don't see your repository here, or you cannot have access to GitLab, send me an email ASAP so I can fix the issue for you.
And then when it comes to what you will submit, so you will be submitting the source code.
The source code for this assignment is worth 50% of the grade for this assignment.
So this includes the source files, the build files for your chosen programming language.
The readme is worth 10% of the grade, so 10 points.
In the readme, you have to write your name, email address, and then the programming language that you chose for this assignment, just like in programming assignment one.
And then the report will be worth 40%.
So in the report, that's where you include the performance evaluation table and the answers to the questions.
And you upload the report on D2L.
Okay?
The readme, I've already included a lot of information on how to compile and run the application.
Only if you need to change things, you need to go ahead and do that.
But otherwise, the readme will remain pretty consistent.
Okay?
So when you submit this assignment, two-step process.
Submit the code first and then the report.
using the timestamp of the report to determine when to grade your code.
Okay.
Any other questions?
So this is again the overview.
What we'll do is we'll spend after this,
if there are no other questions we can go directly,
but after the questions, you know,
what I want to do is I want to spend some time
explaining what this index process is,
what an index is, okay,
and how to conceptually think about implementing this in your application.
Alright, any other questions?
Okay, well, let's try to understand what this search engine thing does.
Because, again, we discussed, right, and we know that if we just want to build a program that just scans the files, right,
that will take 2,000 seconds every single time I want to run a query, which is not very efficient.
So we want to build something else.
It's fast.
So to do this, before we build anything
we need to understand
what an index is
and the best way is to actually first talk about
what a file system is
and we will try to use some mathematical notation
to understand what a file system is
and then it will allow us to understand what an index is
So let's say that I have a file system
and I want to define it in mathematical terms
So if you remember from your math classes, the way we can define a function is by, you know, representing the input domain and the output domain.
And then what is the relation between the input domain and the output domain?
Right.
So this is what we give as an input to the file system and what it gives us as an output.
So a file system, right, has an input domain and an output domain.
The input domain is the domain of document names or document paths in the system.
Right.
So this is what we give as an input to our file system.
Right?
We can have document1.txt, document11.txt, readme.pdf, right?
So these are the documents that are in human readable form, right?
This is the input domain.
Whenever you operate on a file, on the file system, you have to open the file and you've got to give it a path.
And then the output domain is actually the domain of the words that are contained in those documents.
So we can have cats, we can have dogs, tigers, so on and so forth.
And again, the file system is the function that takes us from the domain of file paths.
to the domain of the words that are contained inside that file.
We can have multiple occurrences of a word, right?
So we all know this.
All right, so this reorganization of the data
that will allow us to then do search operations very fast,
to do data retrieval and then information retrieval,
we can think about it conceptually.
So I'm going to call this index, so IDX.
I'm going to use the IDX acronym for it.
So the index, we can define it as approximately the inverse function of the file system.
So the index is a function, a mathematical function,
that has also an input domain and an output domain,
but it's the inverse of the function.
So basically the input domain becomes the domain of the words.
Right, and it takes us to the domain of the documents.
Right, so this is what we want to build when we talk about an input.
We want to build some sort of data structures or algorithm or a combination of both that implements this mathematical function that takes us from the domain of the words to the domain of the documents.
If we have this function implemented, then if we need to search for documents that contains cats and dogs, we can quickly retrieve that list of documents that contains cats.
We can retrieve the list of documents that contains dogs.
And then we just have to do either the intersection or union operation or something to combine.
Okay?
So now, if we want to implement this function,
what would be a great data structure that you've learned, you know,
in previous classes that we can use to implement this exact model?
Yes.
A map or a table?
Yes, a hash map or a hash table.
Perfect, right?
We could also use, for example, a balanced binary tree or something like that,
like an ABL tree or a redback tree.
So any kind of search data structure that provides good, let's say, performance when it comes to doing lookups, because that's what we would be doing.
We do a lookup, the key is the word, and the value is the list of documents that contain that word.
Okay, very good.
So with this information, we can now move forward and start defining what the index is in terms of data structures.
That would be the next step when it comes to designing this application.
And you can apply this model of thinking about application to other complex applications as well.
So I'm going to separate this in half.
And here we will provide the implementation of this index.
So we said we were going to use a hashback.
Let's say, OK, it's the simplest, you know, data structure algorithm to implement the index.
Now, if I remember right, we talked about hash tables last time, right?
Somebody told me I think that a hash table operates on keys and values, right?
So we have a bunch of keys, and we have a bunch of values.
So for this particular index for this assignment, what do we store as keys and what data structure type would be the key B.
Yes?
The keys are just the words and they have a string right?
Correct.
Perfect.
So the keys are the words and they are simply strings.
Alright, what are the values now?
Because the keys, they will point to that.
Yes?
The values would be the documents that include that.
Yes, and what data type will be?
Like a link list might work.
A link list, right, a vector, anything you want.
But it's a list, that's the important part.
So it's a list of documents.
Okay?
Now, if we just store a list for each of these words, the documents, whenever we want to
do a search, this will just give us the list of documents.
So we're just implementing data retrieval.
We're not implementing information retrieval.
So for information, we also need that to Relevance score.
and we said that the relevance score will be the frequency, right?
That's what we would use.
So I'm going to make a correction here in that we will not store a list of documents.
Well, what we will store actually is a list of document frequency pairs, right?
So I will have document1.txt and the number of times cats appears in document1.
Let's say it appears seven times.
then maybe document 11.txt,
and maybe cat appears 23 times.
Okay, and all of the pairs.
And we apply this to all of the key value pairs inside this data string.
All right, so now I want to add an extra detail
that you will need to implement in this application.
And the reason why we need this is because from past experience,
if we design the index in this way, the index will explode in size
because there will be many words that will be contained in many documents,
so the document path will be repeated as a value in the different lists in this data structure.
And unfortunately, the document path can end up becoming pretty long,
so they are going to occupy a lot of space in memory.
I know they say in software engineering that premature optimization is the root of all evil,
so we don't want to do optimizations before we know what's actually going on in the system,
but we need to do this particular optimization.
So we will call this data structure the term inverted index.
I'm inverted because it represents that inversion of the file system function.
Now, in the documentation here, right, I have in the index store, I'm managing a term inverted index.
But I'm also managing this document map.
This is where this optimization comes into play.
To make sure that our index does not blow up in terms of memory utilization,
you will also need to implement a document map,
which is another data structure.
And you can implement this using any kind of data structure you want.
And what this data structure does, it creates a mapping between document IDs and document paths.
So for each document, it will assign an ID, okay?
You can assign these IDs in any order you like, okay, or using anything you like.
And then inside the index itself, instead of storing the file path, we will be storing the document IDs.
So document ID and frequency.
Document ID and frequency.
Okay, so if we store the document ID as a 64-bit integer, how many bytes do I need to use?
Eight bytes, right?
Now if I were to store the path, if it's in slash home, slash AORN, slash workspace, slash projects,
it's already right growing close to 20 bytes.
So this way will allow you to actually have a smaller index.
It's a common technique that people use.
Let's use it as well so that the index can fit in memory.
All right, very good.
So this is what the index store, I'm going to use the IS acronym for it.
This is what the index store needs to manage at the data layer in your application.
It needs to manage two data structures, a term imported index data structure and a document map data structure.
If you can create a program that can, if it receives as an argument some sort of folder,
if it scans to the folder, grabs all of the contents of the folder,
and creates this index in the document map,
will then allow you to now do search operations very efficiently.
So now instead of scanning the entire dataset that takes 2,000 seconds,
in the case of one terabyte dataset,
now what you do is you just run some lookup operations in your index, right,
and you can return probably a search result in about two seconds.
All right.
So very efficient.
You know, modern-day search engines,
they will store this index on disk to have it stored persistently as well.
They have additional operations for the updates as well.
Okay.
This is, of course, things that we can do.
All right.
But now the question is how do we populate?
What are some of the basic, let's say, steps for populating this index store?
What are the, let's say, operations that we have to do at the processing layer?
Okay, so let's go ahead and try to look at the high-level overview of the processes that happen whenever we do index and whenever we do search.
so we know that the processing layer has a index folder method that receives as an argument
a directory path now I'm using directory and folder as synonyms here okay so just bear with
So, in order for this application to build that index, right, we have to do some other smaller discrete steps inside this component.
Step number one, we said that we need to traverse, right, the directory path.
In literature, this process is called crawling.
Crawling can be applied to web data.
You're crawling the web, so you're going from one link to the other, right.
But we can also crawl a file system by going down the hierarchy, starting from a certain point.
So we will apply a crawling operation over the directory path that was given as an argument.
And this will return a list of documents.
Okay.
All right.
This will contain document1.txt, blah, blah, blah, document11.txt, so on and so forth.
Okay.
So out of curiosity, you know, if I were to ask you, you know,
what kind of algorithm or approach would you use to actually do this Scrum?
Knowing that, again, the files in that directory path, they might reside in other sub-directories.
So what strategy would you use to crawl that folder?
You just loop over everything, and if it's a directory, you recursively call crawl again?
Perfect.
So right, so you grab one of the directories, right?
You check to see what are the contents of the directory.
If it's a file, store it in a list, right?
If it's a folder or another directory, call the function recursively or, you know, return afterwards all of the files.
All right, so you can use recursion.
The algorithms that you can use, right, there are two ways you can explore this tree.
You can do a depth-first search versus a breadth-first search, right?
And then if I wanted to ask you, if you don't want to use recursion and you just want to use a loop, actually,
there's a data structure or there are two data structures that you can use to implement this.
Can somebody tell me what are those data structures?
They are a type of list, but they have a special property in the way you add and remove elements from it.
Stack.
Stack. Perfect.
So you can also use a stack in a while-true loop.
The way the stack would work, right, solution, is you would read the first folder, put it in the stack,
then pop the first element for the stack.
If it's a folder, right, grab all of the contents of the folder and add them to the stack,
and then pop another element from the stack.
If it's a file, add it to the list of documents.
If it's a folder, extract the contents, put them in the stack, all right?
So this will allow you to then explore this entire space
without using recursion if you don't want.
All right, very good.
So now that we have these documents, right,
the next step would be to, of course, in order to build this index,
we have to extract all of the words or all of the tokens from the document.
We need to count their frequencies, right,
and then we need to store them inside the index store.
So we need a for loop. So for each document in documents, what we need to do, of course, is we need to extract the tokens from the document.
So again, we know the rules.
We say that whenever we identify, we can scan.
So we read the contents of the documents, scan them byte by byte.
If a byte is a delimiter, then it means I have the beginning and the end of a word.
I read a word until I reach another delimiter.
And then I store all of this data into some sort of list or some sort of dictionary.
After that, step number two is, of course, I need to count the frequencies,
because we need the frequency information, right,
to store in the index.
This, in literature, is called the word count problem.
When you have a document with, you know, various words,
you know, if you want to count the frequencies
of the word, we say that we want to solve
the word count problem.
We typically want to do, actually,
these steps together in one single step.
We don't want to extract the words and then do the counting.
It's usually expensive.
Just do them in one single operation.
Okay.
Now, what would be a great data structure that you can use to store the words and their frequencies when you do the word count operation?
Hashraph?
Hashraph.
Yay.
Bingo.
See, hashmaps are very popular in this class.
All right.
So, we want to store the, let's say, word frequencies.
I'm going to call these WF.
and we'll store them in another hash .
Let's see if this is for document 1.
Okay.
Now that we have the word frequencies,
the remaining steps,
since the index store is using this document map
to create these document identifiers.
We need access to that identifier.
So we will call index store.
And there is a put document function that you need to implement.
You pass the document path,
and this will give you the document ID.
And then the last step is you call index store update index.
You pass the document ID as an argument and the word frequencies as an argument,
and this will go and update this data structure.
The index store is, again, responsible with storing the index and providing lookup operations.
The processing layer is only responsible for doing this computation,
for extracting the tokens, doing the word count, that kind of stuff.
And that's all that you need to do to build an index.
so you receive a folder as an argument
and then you go through this processing steps
and you will have an index build that you can now do search over
any questions here
this is pretty trivial
so now
let's go over the search operation
sorry professor um how are you determining the index for each file
so um so for each file right i uh read the i extract the tokens into a word count
And then I store those words and their frequencies
into some sort of dictionary data structure.
And then what I do is I call index store update index
on the document ID and that word frequency,
which then goes to the index store.
And then the index store is responsible with reading
that word frequency dictionary one key value pair at a time
and updating this term-inverted index data structure.
So it will read.
Where are you?
Yeah, go, go, go.
Oh, but where are you getting the document ID in general?
Oh, the document ID, you want to get it also from the index store
by calling index store put document.
But where does the ID in general come from?
Like how is the ID assigned to the document itself?
This is up to you.
So you can use whatever strategy you want.
The index store is responsible with assigning that ID.
Okay, and we just determine how the index store applies that ID?
Exactly.
So the index store inside the document map data structure
will actually store that mapping between the ID and the document.
You can use it if you want, for example.
You can randomly generate a number, a unique number for each document.
You can use a hash function to generate a unique number.
Or, you can use this property in this assignment.
Your program only has to index the data once, and then you do search order.
You don't have to update the index later.
So, you can also just use incremental document ID numbers.
So, the first document that gets indexed gets document ID 1.
The next document, get document ID, too, so on and so forth.
That's a valid solution, and it will still work.
Cool, thank you.
Yep.
Actually, thank you for reminding me.
I had another question, actually.
So when I insert a new key value pair here,
a new word frequency for a specific document ID,
what do I need to do with this data structure
when I try to insert that element.
So usually you have to determine whether it's there or not.
Correct.
So I need to determine first, do I have a list here or not?
So does the key exist?
And if the key does not exist, then I need to create a key and an empty list
and then I can grab that list and append to that list.
Okay, so just be aware that this is some of the operations that you might need to do in the program, okay?
Because I know we're used to, when we're using hash tables, we're used to working with keys and values that are a data structure that does not have a collection of values.
So there are single term, let's say, data structures.
Usually the key is a string, the value could be a number, another string, something else, or an object.
But you rarely use it as a collection.
of things, okay? So just be aware of that.
Okay.
So now, let's see what would the search operation look like
inside the processing engine.
So the search operation will
receive as arguments a list of words
that are part of the search query. The words, they are processed by
application interface and just passed as a list of words to the
processing end.
So the list of words can have one word, two words, or three words
for the purposes of this application. So now let's see
what do we need to do in order to be able to build those top
10 search results from the index that is now populated after we
did indexing. Alright, well
step number 1 is of course we need to extract first
the list of documents and frequencies for each word.
We need to grab all of those lists first.
So I'll call this wi
in words.
What I do 1.1
is I do an index store
lukov
I pass the word
and this will return to me a list
of document IDs and frequencies.
So if I'm searching for cats, this will return the list
that contains 1 and 7, so document ID 1 and frequency 7
document ID 17 and
frequency 23, so on and so forth.
I can return a copy or a reference
to it, it's up to you, you get to
choose that in your assignment,
in your implementation.
So once we're done with this step, the next
step now, right, is I need to
identify, because
I said that when we do the
queries, the multi-term queries,
these are AND queries.
So we want to return the
documents, right, that
contain at least one occurrence
for each term, right?
If I were to think about what kind of
operation do I need to do over those
lists that belongs
in the area of, let's say,
set operations from mathematics,
what would be the operation that I would
have to do
to combine
these lists?
Intersection.
Destiny,
I think you want to say something
as well.
Or maybe not.
Okay, so we have to do an intersection operation.
This is where the intersection operation is actually a little bit weird in this assignment.
So, we have to do an intersection.
So, we're doing an intersection over all of the lists, okay?
so let's say that if I have you know n words in my query right I have to do an
intersection over each word right for all of this or maybe you know what I can
do it different I can say I need to do an intersection which conceptually or
It's the equivalent of doing li minus 1 intersecting with li intersecting with li plus 1.
If I have three terms.
Okay?
So, what would this...
Let's see, this would be the list, a temporary list.
What would this list look like?
So we're doing an intersection of a pair of, let's say, data structures.
So we have the document ID, but also the frequency for each term.
So L-1 has the documents that word I-1 contains the document, the list I-1 has the documents in which word I-1 was found, and their frequencies.
The same applies for list I contains all of the documents that have word I appearing in those documents, plus their frequencies.
So what we want is because we want at the end,
when we return the results,
we want to return the top 10 results
where the relevant score, the frequency,
is actually the combined frequency of all of the terms in the query.
So the condition is that
I want to include only documents,
let's say document with ID 1,
But I'm only including it here if document 1 contains both word i-1, both word i and word i-1.
So if I have cats, dogs, and tigers, I only want to include the document that contains cats and dogs and tigers at least once in a year.
So let's say the document 1 contains that.
Now, when it comes to the frequency, the way we store the frequency in this list of document and frequencies,
that is the result of the intersection, is we do a cumulative frequency.
So we add the frequency from document 1 for word I minus 1 plus the frequency from document 1 of word I plus the frequency from document 1 of I plus 1.
So let's say that cats appears two times, dogs appears three times in this document one, and then tigers appears five times, the total will be a frequency of 10.
So that's why this intersection will be weird. It's not just grabbing the documents. We also have to do a combination of frequencies.
So this will be 10.
Alright, once you do this, the next step, of course, is you need to now sort the data in descending order by frequency.
Okay, now before you sort the data, my recommendation is that you create a new list.
So I'm going to call this one uppercase T. It's also a temporary list.
And this will be equal to the old list where you replace the document IDs with the document paths.
I'll explain why this is important.
So, it's list T, but you replace document ID with the document path.
You do this by calling indexStore getDocument.
So, you're going to the index store and you're creating the document map.
and you're passing the document ID for each document in this list.
Okay?
Now this secondary temporary list will have now document paths and frequencies.
So step number four, we need to sort this temporary list
and the new resulting list
will be a list that will
be sorted by
frequency first in descending
order, so the frequency that has
the highest value will be
first at the top, and then the lowest
frequency, combined frequency, will be at the bottom
and if two documents
have the same frequency
you have to sort them by
document path in lexicographic
order. So lexicographic
means that you're sorting them
by the ASCII values in document panels.
Most programming languages, if you compare two strings,
they will give you a number.
The number will tell you if they're lexicographically ordered or not.
Okay?
All right, very good.
So now that we have this sorted list,
the final step,
you need to extract from this list
the top 10 results.
So the top 10 results, put them in a data structure,
and send them to the application interface
so that the application interface can print now.
So, this will be the final results.
Okay.
Any questions?
So, these are, again, conceptually, the things that you do.
Now, when you write the programs,
you can write different functions, right?
They might be a little bit more complicated,
especially when you do this intersection,
there are a few strategies that you can use to do it.
You can use while loops to try to automate it
so they can support any kind of number of terms.
You can do that, but anyways, try to give it a try.
See how well this works.
I know, for example, the Java programming language
allows you to write competitors and stuff,
so you can use that kind of solution as well if you want to
to then call the collection sort function,
but you have a very good competitor.
function. Okay. Let's see. It's 7.15. We usually take a break I think at 7.15 until 7.30 and
then we continue. Okay. Let's take a break 15 minutes and we'll come back and we'll take
a look at the skeleton code. Okay.
Yes!
Yes.
Yes, Simon.
So you're okay with me targeting C++ 26.
So for programming assignment one, yes.
I think for programming assignment two.
It's targeting 23 right now.
It's targeting 23.
And I'm trying to remember the reason why.
So if you want to do 26, feel free to modify it.
And as long as the autograder script works,
both on the CI-CD platform that I have in GitLab
and locally to you, then you're good.
But if it fails for some reason,
try to change it back.
I just don't remember why
I decided, because we're using the same
GCC. I think it's because
GCC60
right, to have full support
right, so GCC, so I think by default
I installed GCC15 on all
of the Autobrader
machines, so that's when I know that
I think C++26 is still experimental
for GCC15.
but you know as long as you're not using any like you know crazy functions i think you should be fine
i want to mess around oh you want to mess around yeah that's why i want to target the one give it
a try give it a try and see how it works and if it works then it's fine okay for yeah for here one
i had to bump gcc up to 16 yeah i see okay so even for that you had to bump it okay so bump it and
see what happens. Feel free in the assignment to modify if you need a CMake to this file
to include the extra stuff that you need. Okay. Oh, but you said you needed gcc16, right?
To be able to use it. Yeah, I can say that's one.
Maybe keep it on 23, then create an additional folder here where you have c16.
It's required me to go in the machines and update and then update everything so I think
it might be just easier for you to just create a new and then use the advanced functions.
Out of curiosity, what advanced functions are you using?
with the static reflection stuff, which is pretty cool.
I think there's a lot of cool networking stuff with that.
Verified data shape, compile time and stuff.
Got it.
And then we do threading stuff.
They have the new std execution, which is, you know,
that sounds pretty cool.
I've never used it.
That's not a good idea.
Okay, okay, I understand now.
Yeah.
Just create another folder and feel free to use GCC60 for the other folder.
Implement everything in 23 and then whatever features you can bring.
No, let me put it differently.
If you want, you can still try to do C++ standard 26
with whatever support it has in GCC50.
So if things are still supported, use them.
If not, you might just need to add when you compile an additional flag.
Say experimental enabled or something.
Yeah, I'll try the experimental flag, right?
From the compiler version of Almanach.
Yeah, it's just the easiest solution, yeah.
But try to put the experimental flag,
because I know we had it in the past.
Anyways, over the years, right,
this class evolved.
We went from, I think, you see 12,
I think, to 13, 14, you know.
And we could pass, you know,
for example, to use the file system functions,
you know, to here.
This requires C++17,
but we had to put some flags
for a certain GCC compiler,
So we put in the scene to work, so it was fine.
I'll throw some flags and circle it.
Ok. Sounds good!
Sorry.
Yeah, no question.
Formwork 1.
It's just about these screenshots.
I did it in like a stupid order, where I was trying to do it before the assemble was posted,
like, make the last skeleton run a rust, so I did a few things before taking screenshots, if that makes sense.
So if we do the screenshots that don't, like,
you can see the final one.
Like, skipping adding existing rules,
firewalls active, so it's not, like,
really showing the result of the command.
So my question is, do you want me to, like, redo it?
No, no, so I would say, for example, for this one,
just do sudo efw status, it will print that the rule is there.
So you don't have to show the exact command, you know,
it will be fine.
You know, the greater subtract points, just let me know.
I'll give it back to you.
Okay, for sure.
And then there's no, like, given test cases, right?
Not for programming assignment.
Yes, you have.
But not for assignment.
So you can write your own test if you want to, but it's not mandatory.
And then I also think you were asking me something at the beginning.
Whether we were going to check it on your computer or not.
Oh, I was talking about the quiz questions.
Oh yes, let's check.
I checked right when you said it though.
I don't think it were.
Oh yeah, let's see.
Because I know they're in a weird place.
So if you go to quiz and then you have to go so quiz 1, we'll click on the arrow there
and then if you click on reports.
No.
Go back on it and then submission, let's see.
And then just click on attempt one.
Here you'll be able to see.
just in a weird word.
For my GitLab account, it was deactivated.
Okay, so send me, it's still deactivated now?
Yeah, it's still.
Okay, so send me an email, so that once I'm done with the class,
I'll activate it, and then you'll be able to log in.
Okay.
All right, sounds good.
Is that a Steam Deck or what is it?
Yeah, it's Steam Deck.
Oh, so you brought it as a computer. Nice.
I've been using it as my
computer for school
since the first one came out.
Very nice. I haven't seen it before.
It did cross my mind as well
because I'm like, okay, when I'm in the train
and commuting, you know,
with the laptop
I feel like it's kind of cumbersome
have that space or whatever i'm like clever idea anyways yeah and the touchpad they use the
keyboards is actually really efficient yeah i mean it's linux so you can yeah do whatever you want
yeah and it's been working great i even upgraded the oled one that came out because of how good
the lcd one was nice nice okay how much does the battery hold since it's meant to be playing games
24-7. The battery's huge in this
thing, so if you're just doing basic tasks,
this could last
days without charging.
That's cool.
Great idea. Maybe my next investment
now.
A lot of people bought it
thinking they'll play games on it,
but they have a gaming computer at home.
So the used market for these things are actually
not that bad, price-wise.
I don't know about buying a brand new one
because with the RAM shortage.
yeah I think now everything is expensive
maybe okay maybe once the RAM
stay on
well hopefully it does we'll see
because it doubled in price I bought this for
brand new it was $5.50
now it's $1,000
yeah I believe yeah
things are crazy yeah
I sometimes check prices as well for computers
RAM components you know
again doing
researching systems I kind of want to see what's
the latest architectures and stuff and
RAM yeah it's really
out of control. Anyways,
they increased like more
than doubled, you know, four times sometimes.
Yeah.
Anyways, I think,
I don't know, in the upcoming future,
it's going to become more and more relevant
to actually
learn how to implement programs
with a smaller amount of RAM.
Yeah, exactly.
Even getting a GPU right now,
you cannot find one at MSRP.
No, no.
They're all over.
Yeah.
We're just happy I built my computer before all of this happened.
Yup, yup, yup.
That's good, that's good.
Thank God you had the intuition.
A creative way to use a gaming laptop, is a Steam Deck right now.
I see, that makes sense.
That makes sense.
It's unfortunate, anyways.
As in the end this will slow down with a lot of money.
See, maybe one day, you know, we'll stay alive.
Not in the near future.
I think the next five years.
Yeah, it's going to be rough.
The next five years.
Because we've got to implement more efficient programs.
Maybe there will be a resurgence in compression, you know?
Everyone wants to do it.
Because I think processors are still cheap, right?
Yeah, exactly.
They are expensive.
For how long?
We don't know.
Even computer cases right now are extremely cheap because
we can build a computer right now.
Motherboards as well.
Everything, with the exception of GPUs and memory.
And storage as well.
Yeah, even storage is a lot of price.
Well, fingers crossed.
Hopefully at some point he will return, but in the meantime,
let's use whatever we have.
Yeah, exactly.
and maybe try again to build software more efficiently.
Maybe this is where, again, I don't know if we can compete with how fast, you know,
code can be written, let's say, by AI, as anyone talks about it,
but maybe, you know, you can write code fast,
and that was never really the challenge when it comes to software engineering.
Like, you know, we figured out how to write a lot of code,
and the IDs help and whatever,
but it's like how we write maintainable code,
you know, efficient code, and you know, there are certain things that sometimes as, you
know, software engineers, we know, we just can, we can incorporate more context, I feel
like, you know, with minimal communication, an AI could, because in AI you really have
to give it like, a lot of information, and you can make good decisions, you know, but
I mean, you basically want to go grab a beer with your AI and talk, you know, entire night
to give you all the information so that you can come with the same decision.
That's where we can think more about how do we use the small amount of RAM
that we have now to still program these applications.
I'm hoping that this will be somehow to the better for all of us,
even though it looks bleak.
Let it go to the tunnel.
And it's trying to make an opportunity from a tragedy, let's say.
Yeah, exactly.
And there's some great opportunities right now, especially for making more efficient
programs.
Especially for systems engineers, right, or distributed systems as well, it's becoming
more and more important.
I mean, I know I think that, you know, all of the cloud companies have been setting up these contracts like ahead of time to like, hey, give me the RAM for next year and three years and whatever.
Yeah.
Right.
But the thing is that unless they make the cloud like very cheap, right, when you do the analysis, if you have an application, right, if you just want to run it for like a month, it's not worth buying the computer.
Yeah.
But if you run it over five years, for example, it makes more sense to have one premise, you know, stock.
So I'd be curious to see how that price changes.
They can make it so low that, you know, it takes you 10 years to catch up with the price you can have it on premise.
Maybe it's worth going to cloud.
Yeah.
We'll see.
I don't know what the prices are right now.
It's definitely worth doing the cloud.
It is, right?
How much is a small VM that we use?
I have no idea.
I never looked at the prices for the cloud computing.
It used to be like a couple of cents, you know, per hour, I think?
It could run for like a month, I think, 20 bucks or something.
A decent VM, I think.
Four cores, eight a bytes of RAM.
it is i'm kind of thinking as well you know if you were to run these ai models locally for example
to do software development and stuff you know i mean you can get the 20 per month subscription
so that would be 12 months 240 dollars per year right even if you were to buy like i don't know
a dgx spark or something that's like four thousand five thousand dollars and you know maybe five
So $5,000, I mean, 240, you'll be able to use it for like 20 years.
Yeah, exactly.
That's not really worth it.
No, that's not.
That's unfortunate.
Yeah.
so
I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you,
I'll see you next time.
you
Bye.
Let me go ahead and close the door and let's continue.
Alright, so as I have mentioned, for programming assignment 2, it's more, let's say, programming-oriented, plus we need a more common framework to do auto-grading as well, and to make the grader's life easier, you know,
I've also created some skeleton code.
So what I opened here, this is the root repository from which your repositories were created from.
Okay, so it should look pretty similar, I think, once you look into your repository.
But let's go over a little bit over the skeleton code and see how it identifies with the components of the application that you need to implement.
So the first thing, when you connect to your repository,
again, know that there is a top-level readme.
And then there's a bunch of readmes in these app, cpp, go, java, and rust folders.
So since, again, you're allowed to use C++ or Java or go or rust,
the way that I would do is I would choose the programming language
and then go inside that particular folder that contains the skeletal code for your programming language.
Now if you're feeling you know very adventurous and you know you have a lot of free time you know you can try to implement all of them but make sure that you at least choose one programming language and the readme because that's the one that will be used by auto-graders script.
The auto-graders script will only read the programming languages here but if you contain multiple languages you will fail.
Just include a new one.
So the first step is make sure you update the readme or write your name, email address
just like in programming assignment 1 and the programming language that you chose and
then you can go ahead in the folder that will contain the skeleton code for your chosen
programming language.
So let's start with Java first because it's the easiest one and we'll go over all of them.
So inside the the Java folder you'll see there is another nested readme here.
The readme actually contains the instructions for how I set up for the skeleton code software
tool chain, so what build tools I use, which version of the java development kit I use.
It also has instructions on how to download the datasets.
and just be aware when you access this link,
this will take you to the OneDrive managed by DePaul.
And to be able to download the data sets,
you need to actually log in using your DePaul credentials.
And once you download them on your host computer,
you can then transfer them to your virtual machine
using the commands listed here.
OK.
But I've also included already instructions here
on how to compile the program.
So for Java, I'm going to package the program as a JAR.
And then you can call the program from the jar using the command listed here.
And then you have a bunch of example commands of what would take, you know,
or what kind of output to expect when you're implementing this application.
So please make sure when you implement an application that you try to match this output,
because this is what the autograde the script will look at.
So, for example, here, indexing dataset one.
So this is what the commands would look like when you start the program.
it will print a prompt, then the user will type in the command, and then once the command
is done, the program will print some information and then another prompt.
So here, for example, I printed the number of bytes that the program read when it did
indexing and the total amount of time that it took to do indexing.
So this is the wall time.
This can then be used to calculate the index throughput, for example, for the performance
in the animation.
And then I do some search operations, right?
And these are actual results that you can use to validate the correctness of your program.
There's other queries, of course, that are part of the autograder script that will be able to tell you if your results are correct or not.
Okay.
If you want to use the autograder script, there is instructions here at the VidMem.
You'll need to install Python 3.4.14.
And then these are the instructions for running the autograder script.
So there is a setup script that you need to run first.
that will then clone another repository inside your repository that would be the actual program
that will run the tests okay so um all right so for each of these um implementations we have a
higher level readme that will contain similar instructions so for c plus plus again the tools
that we need to run c plus plus programs with the instructions on how to compile in c plus plus for
go. You have instructions for go.
And then instructions
for lost as well.
Okay?
With examines. Now your programs,
it doesn't matter what programming language you're implementing.
They should return the same results.
Okay? All right. So going
back to the Java,
so
in addition to the readme, you also have the build
file. In this case, this is a
maven build file that contains the instructions
on how to compile the code.
And then the source code, you'll find it under source, main, Java, cc435, app.
And then here you will have four source files.
Now three of the source files will contain the implementation of the layers of your application.
So if you go back to the description, your application has three layers, application, interface, processing, engine, index, store.
For each of them, you have to create a class.
So Java will use object-oriented programming,
like Phoenix for implementing the application,
and then you need one more class to include all of these objects or all of these layers.
Okay, so that's why you have four source files.
The main function resides in the file retrieval engine.
So this is your entry point in your program.
It has the public static void main,
and this is where the layers are created as objects.
So then, for example, for the application interface to be able to use the services provided by the processing engine layer, of course, we pass a reference of the processing engine to the application interface object.
Okay?
This is what the constructors do, let's say, in Java.
And then the program basically calls the application interface read commands, which basically creates a while table that just reads the commands until the user types in the quit command.
so we can take a look so this is your entry point in the application interface right you need to
implement the application related functionality of your program there are two of course to do
comments here which tells you what do you need to implement inside this function okay so here for
example you just need to implement the parsing of the index command and search command and then you
have to call the proper method inside the processing engine for a processing engine
you have some helper classes here
that can help you store intermediate
or the data that you're going to work with.
And then the process engine itself implements only two methods
according to the specification of the assignment,
so search and index folder.
And then the to-dos here contain instructions
on how to implement index and search,
similar to the way we define it on the whiteboard
using, again, let's say abstract notation.
And then the index store is responsible with actually storing the document map and the term we've earned in the index.
And we're providing methods that allow you to actually update and do lookups over these two data searches.
Okay.
Just follow the to-do's.
There are two ways you can implement this assignment.
You can follow a top-down approach where you implement the application interface first, the processing engine, and then the index store.
That's fine.
You can also do bottom-up where you do index.for first,
then processing engine, then interface, you know,
middle out, whatever you want.
You can use any kind of approach.
All right.
If we want to go, for example, to the C++ implementation,
again, it follows a similar structure.
We use CMake to compile the C++ code.
And then since this is C++,
Plus we split the declaration of the class from the implementation of the class.
So we have header files for each of the layers and then source files for each of the layers.
Plus the file retrieval engine CPP files where we have the int main function.
Now if you're implementing it in C++, you will see that I've used here the shared pointer.
Let's see, smart pointer implementation.
If you don't want to use the shared pointer, that's fine.
you can replace this with a traditional pointer.
Just so that you know that it's pretty standard practice, I think,
to use smart pointers nowadays in C++
and to try to use resource acquisition is initializations
or RAI is the acronym.
So it's basically a way to automatically manage memory in C++ as well.
So if you've never used them before,
my recommendation is that go and check them out on cppreference.com
and learn how to use them
because if you interview in C++,
it's highly probable that people will ask you,
hey, what's a shared pointer?
What's the difference between a shared pointer,
a unique pointer, and a weak pointer?
So it will be useful for you to learn how to use it.
But then when it comes to the implementation,
again, very similar to the Java code,
the only difference, again,
you have header files and source files.
But you still have to do so.
And the structure of the code is very similar, actually,
between C++ and Java.
So we're still using object-oriented programming here as well.
Now things will be different once you go to Go and Rust
because they don't have, you know, the ability to create classes, right, per se.
They don't have object-oriented features, but you can create structs
and you can create methods for your structs.
So we're using structs to encode, let's say, the structure of the application.
So in Go, the entering point is the file retrieval engine.go source file.
This is where you're creating variables for each layer, you're passing references to those
variables so that they can call each other, and then you call the readcommands method
in the application interface structure.
Right, and then similar here to C++ and Java, you have to-dos that you have to fill out
to implement the various parts of your program.
it's a common practice but it's not mandatory
to create constructor functions in Go
so since Go uses has structs in our classes
there is no requirement to create a constructor function
but it's very typical in programs for developers
to create these factory
let's say create functions that can create objects
of a specific data structure type
So feel free to, if you want to remove this, if you want to keep it more pure, you can do that.
Again, it's not mandatory, but it's common practice to do it.
Okay, so feel free to modify this if you need to.
Let's see, processing engine, right?
You still have these, you know, helper data structures that you can use, of course.
And then the same kind of tools that you have in the other languages as well.
And lastly, for Rust, you have a cargo build file.
So, you can use cargo to compile the Rust program.
You can see examples here on how to do it and how to execute the code.
And then the source code is organized similar to the Go programming language.
So, your entry point will be the file retrieval engine.
And then here, again, similar to Go, Rust does not have built-in capabilities for object-oriented
programming.
So you can use trait, and you can create methods for structures, right.
But you don't have inheritance, and other stuff.
But you're not really using that in the case.
So just be careful here with Rust.
Again, if you're going to use it, I'm assuming you're going to have some basic knowledge about it.
Just be careful.
In this skeleton code, when I create the various components, right, I'm passing them as arguments.
And if you remember from Rust, or if you know, Rust uses move semantics.
semantics. So, basically, the ownership
of the object gets moved now into another
object. Okay, so just be careful.
This will change for the next assignments
when we have multiple threads because
multiple threads will need access to the same
object. Okay, so just be very
careful. But otherwise,
the structure is the same. Again,
by convention, you don't have to have a
constructor in Rust,
but people usually create this new function
that allows you to then create
new structures in a very
standardized way.
okay but otherwise the code looks very similar to the other languages just
follow the to-dos you can implement it in whichever order you want and then
lastly the last folder is the test folder that contains a Python script that
basically clones the autograder RepalStory and then allows you to run the
autograder script I did it this way in case you know there are bugs in the
autograder script it allows me to fix the bugs and then when you run set up
Again, it just synchronizes the code for you.
So the code is not embedded inside this repository.
Okay.
Make sure there is an expectation.
So when you run the autograder script,
the autograder script expects you to have the datasets,
so datasets 1, 2, and 3,
stored in the root of the repository in the datasets folder.
So you need to create a datasets folder here
and we'll copy the data into the datasets folder.
So you'll be able to see if I go to the readme here,
this is what this readme is trying to tell you,
that you need to create the datasets folder
and then copy the datasets inside the datasets folder.
The Autograder script will let you know
if you cannot find the data sets, okay?
But know that this is the, in a sense,
expectation there for the Grader script.
All right, and what we use in this class is we also use CICD features in GitLab.
So that's continuous integration, continuous development.
What this means is that whenever you push your code to your repository,
the GitLab server will automatically contact one of the worker servers
and will actually run the autograder script for your code.
So that's why it makes sure that you update the programming language to your own language
so that the GitLab server can know which programming language to test.
And you can access to see, for example, the results of the auto-grader,
let's say, one on the GitLab server by going on the left menu here.
If you go under Build and then if you go under Jobs,
you'll be able to see the list of jobs.
If you open up the most recent one, it will show you the output of the GitLab runner or worker program.
In this case, what it did is clone my repository, and then it basically ran the setup script, and then it run the test script.
So when you run the setup script, it will clone the autograder repository.
And then when it runs the test script, it will actually test your program.
In this case, for me, the autograder is throwing an error
because the skeleton code doesn't have one programming language, you know, chosen there.
But if I were to change this, it will run through all of the tests.
The tests are basically, are just testing to see if your program is working correctly on dataset 1.
So it tries to see if you index it correctly,
and then if the results of the search commands are correct.
Okay, the performance, that's something that you will need to do
when you do the performance evaluation
and you do it on your computer
and you have to test it
with data set 1, 2, and 3.
But the autograder only looks at data set 1
because it's smaller
and it doesn't take a lot of time.
Okay?
I was going to say one small detail here.
So for programming assignment 1
you may use your personal computer
to run the evaluation.
I'm not sure if we're going to do it
with programming assignment 3 or 4
but I'll give you access at some point
as the portal progresses to Chameleon cloud.
So you will be able to actually test
or do the performance evaluation
on more powerful machines on Chameleon cloud.
Chameleon cloud is a bare metal cloud,
so you get access to a bare metal machine,
and their machines, they have, you know,
64 to 120 cores and 120 gigabytes of RAM.
This is, again, DDR3,
so it's not going to be really as fast
as maybe your modern-day computers,
but it has huge capacity.
In programming assignment 3,
what you will be doing is
we're trying to improve your program,
improve your application,
so to improve the indexing performance of your application
by using multi-threading techniques.
So you can try to see, you know,
if you want to increase the number of threads,
you know, from 1 to 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64,
you can see on those machines how well your program works.
Now on your machine, you're going to be limited
by how many cores you have on your system.
All right, and then the last aspect is the data sets
that I need to show you so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna access the link
the programming assignment from the readme let's do rust there's a link here
let me open up this link so this will connect me to one drive and I think I'm
already logged in with the school address and these are the datasets okay
So there are six datasets in total, but for programming assignment two and three, you just need data set one zip, two zip, and three zip.
Okay.
The client servers are for programming assignments four or five in the extractive assignment.
So let me just go ahead and download one of these so I can show you what it's like.
You can, again, copy them to your virtual machine, archive, and then there is an unzip command that you can install on Ubuntu by doing should have to install on zip.
which then will allow you to unzip the archive directly into a virtual machine.
But for here, I'm just going to extract it here.
So all of the data sets are organized at the highest level in the same way,
and there's a reason why we do that.
So if I go in data set 1, you will see that in data set 2 and 3 as well,
there will be eight folders,
And then inside these folders, you will have documents and other folders.
And they are organized in a very unbalanced way.
Okay.
So you'll need to do this, you know, recursive traversal of the documents.
And then all of the documents will be TXT documents.
So you don't have to worry about, oh, will I encounter some sort of binary file that I'm allowed to index, right?
They're all formatted in ASCII format.
Okay.
And I think they're all formatted to use the Linux new line.
If you remember from System 2, I think, right,
Windows uses a different way to represent new lines,
uses the backslash R backslash M,
while Linux uses the backslash M.
So this is a Unix format.
Okay.
All right.
Any other questions regarding the assignment?
I don't.
Oh, yes.
It's only kind of related but are we still going to go over how to connect like an IDE
to the to the guest machine?
Oh, yeah, that's a good point.
So you're allowed to use these IDs and code editors.
What I can do.
I can show you right now how to connect to your VM or like a remote machine using VS code.
and now if you use something else
so for example if you're using the
JetBrains tools they usually
have built in support for remote development
nowadays I think if you use
Nitro Love Studio
also has built in support
Eclipse has built in support but then
if you use something else I might not know
but I can just show you VS Code Hive works
so to do that
I'm going to try to see if I can
share my screen on my laptop
but let me actually
make sure that I'm not leaking my emails here.
I've been using Mutagen.
The command line tool to sync the directories
between the remote machine and my local machine.
Okay.
And so then I just use my local ID and when I save a file,
then it pushes it to the robot.
What is it called?
Mutagen.
It's on, are you on a Mac?
Yeah.
It's on Homebrew I think.
okay
so let's see so i'm sharing
all right so i think i'm sharing this screen right now which is very good so what i'm gonna
do is i'm gonna open vs code and as i'm using linux here this is a you know standard uboon
implementation. All right, so then in VS code, VS code by default does not have
support for remote development so you'll need to install an extension. So if you
go to extensions here, and then you search for extensions. Oh but it's not. Oh I see
it's only shared on zoom but it's not shared here. Not bad. Let me think about
I'll come back next time and I'll see if I can do something here or if I can connect this laptop to
Do you have an HDMI port? I do yeah, I do have an HDMI port so I should be able to
connect but there is a way where I can tell actually the system
to show things from zoom there anyways let me try to see if I can connect the HDMI
Give me one moment so that I can stop sharing actually this one but then when I
stop sharing that one this doesn't share anymore so I need to share here.
Share to me to me.
Perfect.
So this came back.
Now let me see HDMI.
Actually, it's HDMI.
Let's see if this will work.
So I can leave this but then I also have to tell it that I'm going to use the HDMI.
oh and I need to make it so that this is not extended
display mirror all right perfect
so now let's see if we can do VS code back the only thing with VS code is I need to
increase the size of the font of the interface because it's very small here.
I usually have some profiles... Oh they are density. So very good question how do I
make so I can make the font size larger and I'm not sure how to make the
make the interface larger. Anyways just bear with me maybe when you look at the
recording zoom in, okay so you can see the details here but basically what you
want to do in VS Code is you want to go to extensions and then here search for
the remote extension and they have a remote development extension pack. So if
you go to this one if you install it you will install some additional extensions
including the remote SSH extension, so once you have this extension installed, a
new button will appear on the left called Remote Explorer. So if you go to
Remote Explorer this will show you a list of machines that you have
configured in your .SSH configuration file. It might be empty at the beginning,
but you can always add a new connection. So if you go to SSH, it's plus here, you
You can add a new connection.
And then here, when you add a new connection, you can just type in the exact same command that you use from the command line to connect from the host to your virtual machine.
Right.
So let's say that I want to connect to SSH.
Let's say that I want to connect to telos.cdm.depaul.edu.
This is, let's say, my virtual machine, but it's actually a server somewhere.
But it's still remote development.
Right.
I can press Enter.
you can choose where do you want to store the configuration
this configuration
the host is added
so once the host is added you can connect to it by clicking on this arrow here
which will then authenticate you on the machine
and for me
I have this machine added as a rule so you can authenticate automatically without
asking for a password, I have password list based authentication setup
so then you can see in the lower left corner here
it will tell you that you are connected through SSH
to the TELOS machine.
So whatever you're editing in your editor
will actually be modified directly in the storage
of your virtual machine or your remote machine.
Okay, so you can go down to file, open folder,
and you should be able to see the folders inside your VM,
and you can edit the code from there.
So in a similar way, that's how I think
the other IDs will work as well.
Or if you want to use your solution, that's fine as well.
Okay, switch back over here.
Any other
questions?
Okay.
I was going to say, I know maybe you're still thinking about
programming assignment one, okay?
So make sure you complete that one. Focus on that one.
Try to finish it ahead of time if you can.
Make sure you can access your QRO account.
If not, send me an email as soon as possible.
I'll go ahead and activate your accounts for you.
Again, you're going to have a few days to go ahead and register
and set up your password and 2Fact.Authentication,
but make sure that you do that.
Make sure you do that before the weekend, okay?
I'll be active on Fridays.
I'll watch emails and I'll reply to them.
And then once you're done, you know, if you need to,
you can come back to the actual recording for Programming Assemble,
where you can go ahead and look at the skeleton code with, okay,
the instructions, you know, the details if you want.
but what I've covered today
covers again some of the
let's say high level overview of the assignment
there are no like oh small details
that you gotta be careful for
I've already mentioned them today
but
if there are no other questions
what I want to do tonight for the rest of the lecture
is to start talking about
architectures because you will need to
implement a specific architecture in this assignment
and we'll see this architecture
will then be implemented in the rest
of the
assignments as well.
So, when it comes to architectures, I just want to mention one thing.
So the book calls them architectural styles.
So we got to define what is an architecture.
Basically, architecture is formulated as a set of components that have well defined
interfaces and then we describe how are these components connected to each other, how data
is exchanged between the components and then how the components and the connectors are
are jointly configured into a system.
So, we use the notion of a connector.
So, the connector, it's a special kind of component
that mediates communication, coordination, cooperation.
We'll focus in this class more on the communication part,
but we'll cover coordination as well.
So, it can be implemented in various ways.
But, we'll spend more time on the connector technology
as well in chapter 4.
So when it comes to architectures, we need to distinguish between two kinds of architectures.
So I know we talked at the beginning in the introduction of some of the misconceptions.
We said that some people would say that, oh, a centralized solution is not very great.
But centralized can mean either logically centralized or physically centralized.
Physically centralized means you have one computer.
logically means the service is logically one single
service. But you can have a centralized
system that is logically centralized but physically
distributed. So when we talk about architectures
in this class, we'll talk about both logical architectures
or software architectures and then physical or hardware
in terms of how you organize a distributed
system. So let's start first with
logical architectures or software architectures.
And the most popular architecture out there is, of course, the layered architecture.
This is the easiest one to understand.
And this architecture has been adopted in a wide range of applications, not just in computers.
Layering is the name of a technique that can be used to break down complexity.
This is how we even implement operating systems nowadays.
They are implemented under the form of layers.
You have the hardware layer at the bottom, then on top of it you have the kernel layer
that manages the hardware, provides the process, virtual memory and file abstractions.
On top of it you have some sort of shell or desktop user interface, where the shell could
be a command line shell or it could be a graphical user interface that allows users to then interact
with the resources of the computer.
And then on top of that you have the applications.
This is an example of a layered architecture.
is also used in communication protocols and we'll talk more once we talk about
communication distributed systems how the internet protocols are organized and
what we can use to implement distributed applications now when it comes to
layered architecture the most common form of architecture of layered
architecture is the request response down call architecture so this
This architecture implements multiple layers.
Each layer is responsible with a certain part of the functionality of the application.
And they have a strict hierarchy where the layer on top only contacts the layer on the bottom.
And then that layer only contacts its own layer.
And we have usually some sort of request that goes to the layer and then the response that comes back to the layers.
But the layer on top does not contact a separate layer somewhere else.
So this is very typical in computer networks.
The communication protocol is following this approach.
You can also have layered architectures called one-way call, layered architectures, where a layer can contact layers, not just the layer underneath, but also layers that sit multiple levers underneath.
If you want to think of an example of an application that uses this, let's say that this layer on the bottom is the layer that implements the system calls of an operating system.
And then layer n-1 rotates a library that implements, let's say, matrix multiplication and operations on a matrix, including storing the matrix on disk, which then means that that library needs to make calls to the kernel, needs to make calls to layer n-3.
Let's say that layer n-1 is an application, then, that, you know, operates on matrices.
So then can, you know, use the functions provided by layer n-1 by the library, but also does its own system calls to the operating system.
Okay.
It doesn't have to be too complicated.
And then lastly, you can also have layered architectures where you support upcalls.
So, for example, you have a layer that can either send a request to another layer,
or you can register some sort of notify operation
so that when layer n-2 has some sort of data,
you can do an up call to the upper layer
or you can send a signal to the upper layer
to let it know that the data is available.
This type of layer architecture is very popular
when it comes to the implementation
of input-output operations in operating systems, right?
So if I were to ask you when it comes
to operating systems, right,
What are two ways that you can implement, let's say, the function of reading data from a file from disk?
We know that the disk is very slow, right?
So the program has two options here when it's waiting for the data that comes from the disk.
Do you happen to know what those two strategies are called?
Polling and interrupt, right?
So polling means that the program will stay awake and will try to keep on asking the operating system,
hey, is the data here yet? Is the data here yet? Is the data here yet?
Which means that it might use CPU time while being scheduled by the operating system.
So it might not be a very efficient, let's say, solution unless your device is very fast.
So it's more common in supercomputer architecture where the network devices are actually pretty fast.
Or you can do interrupts, right, where the process tells the operating system,
hey, I want that data from there, and then the process goes to sleep,
and then the operating system sends a signal to the process to wake it up.
This is the equivalent of that up call in a sense
where it sends a signal to the upper layer to let it know that,
hey, things are already there.
We'll talk more about communication protocols,
what's important when it comes to communication protocols.
Oops.
When it comes to communication protocols,
usually
you hear the terms
protocol, service and interface
they have very specific
meanings and we know
that communication protocols between
two entities
are implemented into multiple
layers so we say that each layer
has its own interface that it provides
to either application or
layers as if above
we say that
a service
represents the interface provided by a layer
that sits at a specific level.
And then a protocol refers to how the data is being transferred
between the same layer between two parts.
And then we say that a protocol stack
is when you have a bunch of protocols
that sit one on top of the other in a layered fashion.
We'll talk more about communication protocol and communication.
So we can, for now, skip it.
And then when it comes to layered architecture,
another very popular way to present, let's say, a layered architecture,
especially in modern day applications,
is, of course, the implementation of the application layering architecture.
So here, as I mentioned, this is, again, a traditional pre-layered architecture
where we split the application into three layers.
We have an application interface layer
that is responsible with managing the interface for users
and external applications.
So in addition to a graphical user interface,
a web interface, a command line interface,
it could also be an API as well,
application programming interface.
The processing layer then is responsible
with containing the actual logic
of how the application is implemented
without specifying the data,
and then the data layer contains that information.
so this
layering is
found in
distributed
information
systems
especially
the ones
that use
databases
so
whenever you
hear about
web applications
they are
typically
implemented
by following
this three
layered approach
you might
have heard
already
of a
full stack
developer
front end
back end
developer
so the
front end
is the
equivalent
of the
application
interface
the back
end
is the
equivalent
of the
processing
layer
and the
database
because usually websites are built with the database in mind, the database sits at the data layer or represents the data.
Now, I just want to make a small parenthesis here.
I'm sure you might also have heard about another architecture, but they represent something else.
So you might have heard of the model view controller architecture, which is very popular in web development.
So Model View Controller, where you implement your application by having a model component, a view component, a controller component.
So this is how modern day websites or graphical user-based interfaces are implemented.
And this architecture, it's not necessarily a layered architecture because it follows a cyclical, let's say, architecture.
So the model view controller architecture tries to say that when you implement an application,
the view part of the application, which will be the interface,
will always be updated whenever the model gets updated.
The user sees the view and then operates on the view
to trigger functions on the controller part of the application
and the controller part, the processing layer that does some sort of processing,
and then modifies the data.
So it modifies the model of the application, which then updates the view.
So this is meant to represent the cycle of modifications
inside your application.
Again, a very popular architecture,
but it's different than the application layer.
But they're compatible with each other,
so you can have both of them at the same time.
Again, a very simple example would be with a search engine
where the user interfaces were.
You process the query, or anyways,
you process the tokens that are being passed,
you parse the tokens from the query,
then you pass them to some sort of processing level server
that generates the query, and then you ask a database,
and then the database will give you some answers.
You'll use some sort of ranking algorithm to create the results
and send them back to the user interface that will then be presented to the user.
Anyway, very simple to understand.
So there's one main disadvantage of this layered architecture.
So the main disadvantage is that it's very strict.
Okay, so again, the layers are top.
will depend on the layers on the bottom.
It does not really allow you to have, let's say,
more complex form of dependencies.
And then what happens here is that if you think about the dependability
goal of distributed systems, we say that the component depends
on another component.
And if we follow this layer architecture,
it means that all of the layers, excluding the last layer,
depend on the most bottom layer of the system. So it creates a strong
dependency here. This is something that maybe we want to avoid sometimes in
systems. Maybe we want to have more flexibility on how the dependency that
say hierarchy gets created. So for this, people have explored a different class
of logical architectures in distributed systems. Sometimes these class of
of architectures are called object-based styles or service-oriented architectures.
So now here, instead of creating these strict layers,
what we do is we create various components, right,
and we express the dependency by having components call functions of other components.
So this looks a lot like object-oriented programming.
So we can design a distributed system that is made out of multiple components,
and then the components can make calls to other components,
but they don't have to follow this strict hiring.
So they're more fluid.
This can be, of course, implemented, and that's why whenever you see this architecture,
you typically see object-oriented programming designs as well there.
Object-oriented programming works very well because it clearly separates, you know,
the state and how you modify the state from the interface on how you access, let's say,
a specific object or a specific service, right?
So if you remember, one of the more important properties of object-oriented programming was encapsulation.
So if we can build services that are also well encapsulated, where, again, modifications to the state can happen through very well-defined interfaces, then we will have very good systems.
So you can have, of course, distributed systems where the services are organized as these objects or components that manage their own states and they can be accessed through different interfaces or through their custom interfaces and they can be accessed in a different way.
Now, one of the main problems of implementing an object-based style architecture or a service
variant is that all of the components that need to talk with another component, they
need to know what are the details of the interface of the component that they want to talk.
So imagine if these components are actually designed by different teams.
They have one software engineering team that maybe works on one part of the application
and then another team that works on another part, right?
And they have to have now knowledge
about each other's interfaces.
And we know that sometimes interfaces change, right?
Sometimes we need to update them.
Sometimes we need to change them.
Sometimes we add features,
which means that if we change the interface
of one of these object implementations,
we have to let the other objects know
that the interface has changed, right?
So this creates a cascade of modifications in the system.
So one of the challenges was, you know,
can we implement some sort of general interface for service-oriented architectures?
A way where it makes it very easy for us to change that code
without having to recompile the entire program.
So this gave birth to, and I'm sure you've heard this term,
of REST APIs or REST architectures.
So RESTful architectures are a type of service-oriented architecture
that is, again, very popular, especially over the web.
that has a very interesting way of organizing, let's say, resources
and access to resources in a distributed system.
So now, instead of creating these components that act as objects
that have interfaces in state, people notice that what we need, actually,
in a Cynid-distributed system, or what we want,
is to just modify certain resources in it,
certain data resources most of the time.
In web applications, I'm just accessing a website,
or I'm changing a row in the database.
So I'm just accessing some resources there.
So then they thought about another organization
and REST stands for representational stage transfer.
So this REST architecture follows the following,
let's say, philosophy.
So you view the distributed system
as a collection of resources
that are individually managed by different components,
but we don't necessarily care about the details of the components,
and the resources may be added, removed, retrieved,
or modified by remote applications.
There are, of course, a few properties here.
To have a REST system, you have to make sure
that the resources are identified through a single naming schema.
So on each website, you need to have a unique naming schema
to be able to identify each resource uniquely.
You're not allowed to have and be viewed it.
All of the services, all of the components, they offer the exact same interface for working or interacting with the resources.
So you cannot change the way you call functions to add and remove.
They have to be, again, the same interface across all services.
The messages sent to or from a service are fully self-described.
So when you send one of these operations or you call one of these interfaces, let's say,
you include the details on how you want the operation to be calculated,
but it's part of the message, not part of the interface.
And then after executing an operation at a service,
the component forgets everything about the car,
so we don't store any state about it.
So the basic operations that are supported in the rest architectures
are, of course, the put, get, beat, and post operations.
So, if you have ever implemented any kind of website, you probably have used these operations
because website technology relies actually on, let's say, a REST architecture or a RESTful
architecture.
So, to create a new resource, you'll need to use the PUT function.
So, these are the name of the operations or of the functions that are available as part
of the interface of all of the services.
So, you can create a new resource using the PUT operation.
You can retrieve the state of a resource by using get, delete a resource by using delete,
and then modify a resource by using posts.
So let's see some examples of differences if we were to implement the same distributed
system by using a REST interface versus using an object-oriented interface.
So let's say that we are Amazon and we want to implement a way for people to be able to
store data under the form of objects, right?
This is called Amazon Simple Storage Service, or S3, that you can go and access today, and you can pay money to be able to store objects in their cloud.
Another example of a system that does the same thing is, of course, Dropbox.
A very interesting side note here, historical side note.
In the early days of Dropbox, because storage was so cheap, actually Dropbox was just a web interface that ran on top of Amazon S3.
So they store everything in Amazon and just provide some web interface to do some additional functionality.
Until it became infeasible for them to use S3 because S3 became more expensive.
So then they build their own system.
But at the beginning, they just ran a wrapper on top of S3.
That looked nice.
One quick way to make cheap money with it, right?
Alright, so the way Amazon S3 works...
It allows you to store objects that need to be placed inside the bot.
You can think about these objects kind of equivalent of files and buckets the equivalent
of directories.
The only difference is that you cannot have buckets inside buckets.
OK, so you can have directories inside directories in a file system, but not here.
So you can only have buckets and then objects inside buckets.
So then what Amazon did in order to implement the REST interface, is of course, they need
to provide a unique way to identify all of the resources in their system.
So what they did to uniquely identify the resource is they used actually the URL that you punched in in your, let's say, web browser, or punched in into your program.
They used the URL information to actually determine the unique location of an object.
So the way this works, they use a subdomain for the bucket name.
They include it underneath S3 and AmazonAWL.com and then slash.
And then here they include the object identifier or object name.
Okay, so this is their unique way of identifying objects inside S3.
So now you can use those typical REST operations to actually interact with the objects or with the buckets.
So you can create buckets by doing a put operation along with the URL.
So if you want to create a new bucket, let's say, you do put http colon slash slash the name of my bucket,
which will be my, let's say, video game screenshots, .s3, .amazonaws.com.
if I want to list the objects in a bucket
I will do a get operation over HTTP
let's say video game screenshots
on Amazon AWS.com
and then the service implementing these functions
will know how to return those values
if I want to create an object
I will do the same foot command
the same URL but I would add slash
and then the name of the object
that I want to include there
keep in mind that in S3
the objects are considered to be blobs of data
So Amazon S3 does not do any kind of processing to distinguish between binary data and human readable data.
Okay, everything is binary for it.
Okay, so again, this would be, if we want to, again, to use REST, right,
this is how Amazon S3 organizes resources, and those are the functions that can be used to interact with that resource.
It's very easy, you can use the same approach for implementing services inside a distributed system of your choice.
But Amazon S3 also provides an object-oriented interface.
In this context, it's called a SOAP interface or some sort of API.
They allow you to use Python, for example, and interact with the services using a Python API.
Now, the problem here, or not a problem, but in order to interact with all of the resources provided through this API,
Amazon had to provide actually a bunch of functions.
So this is very different than the rest interface.
So now in order to create the buckets, to list the buckets,
I would have separate functions that need to be implemented,
which means that now when we write a program, we have a choice.
So we can write a program using the object-oriented interface.
So we import, for example, whatever packages Amazon has implemented in Python,
and then we import the proper packet, and then we can call bucket create,
bucket list, and all of the other operations.
Or we can use the REST interface by simply doing an HTTP call using either a PUT operation or a GET operation or DELETE or OKPOST to work on the data.
So now the question is, what are some advantages and disadvantages of using them?
So when using, for example, an object-oriented interface, the advantage is that I can check to see if the calling of the function is correct before I actually submit the function.
So for example, if I did bucket create, but instead of a string, it has some sort of number or some sort of weird data, it can be detected before I even contact the server.
So this is one advantage.
But the disadvantage is that if Amazon one day decides to change the interface, so instead of bucket create decides to do something else, it means that now I have to update my program as well.
The rest interface, the check has to be done on the server side.
if there are any errors.
However, if they decide to change the interface,
right, or the way that they process buckets, right,
they cannot change the interface itself, actually.
Right, so the rest interface remains the same.
I still do the put operation over the same URL
that uniquely identifies the resource.
If I need to add any additional information,
it will be part of this message.
But that can be easily changed.
Instead of writing code,
you just update the way you send the messages
when you send these requests to the server.
So again, there are advantages and disadvantages in using them.
So these usually take more time to process
because we're sending everything in human-readable text formats,
so you have to convert them,
especially if you have complex data structures.
So these are easier to use from a program.
When it comes to changing interfaces or updating how they work,
the REST interface has higher advantages
because it maintains a standard interface.
You just have to add more information to your message.
as long as the URL remains the same
and the functions remain the same?
Professor?
Yes.
So in the spring framework
or just building web applications with Java,
it's got the MVC architecture,
so technically object-oriented,
but then in the controller layer,
you say get or put or post delete.
So is that just a combination of the two?
Yeah, so these layers can also be implemented where you basically, instead of doing API requests to the model, right, or do API requests from the view to the controller, you can actually do REST requests.
So each of these components can be implemented as a REST service.
So then you can do put get operations on them.
Cool, thank you.
So keep in mind that this is mostly, again, a logical organization.
So you can create, again, multiple layers.
You're not stuck with only one layer.
You can create a set of layers.
And usually a distributed application is made out of multiple layers combined,
multiple logical layers, but also multiple physical layers as well.
Okay.
Alright and then the last part, and I think what I want to do, if I think I actually I
wanna stop here and we can talk about coordination and the last let's say popular logical layer
next time.
but i can take a few more questions if we have regarding assignments or regarding
quizzes class content you know if not i want to end here actually i don't want to go too far ahead
i can give you 10 minutes to you know try to attend the quiz if you want to take it now
but if not i can try to answer the questions and activate your accounts as well for students that
send me an email okay but i want to end actually the lecture here
too much and we can continue next time
we'll talk about it and we'll talk about the physical
architectures as well
okay
so we can end the
thank you
yep
That's fine, for programming assignment 1 it's fine.
For programming assignment 2, see if you can just use the one.
That's why we don't have automated training.
So it's by design, you know, it's good that you explore to see how it's run, but then
once you go to programming assignment to see if you can stick with this.
Well, I'm going to spend some time answering the emails, okay, so I can activate the accounts,
okay, but if you have any other questions, just interrupt me, I'll do more than that.
Sorry for the abrupt end, and I kind of realized that I was moving too fast.
Oh
I'm going to get a little bit of stuff.
Thank you.
Okay.
so
Yeah you do.
I think I'll see you.
I'm just working on a scholar, and I've already done for a woman's program.
And so I arrived back to Chicago on a Saturday, and I called them on Monday to site him from
I won, until I get a new one, and they said they discontinued that program.
And the thing is, the cost of computers were up at the point of my brain.
I'm kind of waiting to see when the computer comes in.
Because right now, the same price for it is a lot of time.
so I was really and I was thinking I'd be working on them.
So right now I'm not really stuck on the assignment.
Yeah, I got it.
Well, I can give you an extension for this assignment but try to get a computer because
you need one to complete the assignment.
Yeah, assignments, yeah.
And it doesn't have to be really the most powerful computer there.
So you're saying that the default doesn't go on laptops anymore.
My fault, I don't have that because it's so this is.
Yeah, I know they use computer.
Is there all the beauty yet?
Yeah.
And they were helpful when my computer started working last quarter, I was able to use theirs
and I'm so shocked that they're not doing it anymore.
And then when I asked what you said call the library and I called the library and he said
they only have the news and that one's only for two weeks and also like it's not really
available so I have to keep checking it out.
And I tried little like the lab studios, that would not work because I have to install them
on YouTube but it would need administrator control.
So you cannot install DMs and stuff.
Well try to see if you can get a computer as fast as possible.
Maybe if you have a friend as well, that is not in this class you can borrow their computer
do assignments. This shouldn't take you more than a day to go over it. See if you can do
that while you're waiting for the computer. Again, just keep me posted on how it goes.
Any more time, just let me know, and they will give you a week extension.
And I was also thinking, if I should go back to the library again and ask them for the
news like that, if they should be able to see me through assignment one or two. But
obviously, I'm going to ask them while I'm there, can I install stuff on it.
Yeah, I think if you get a loaner, I think you can. Or if you go to the library and if they have somebody there, you can tell them
you can install this for me. Because you just need the hypervisor. Once you get the hypervisor, then you can install the ends, that should be fine.
So I would go there again tomorrow and hopefully they see something, so far that's what they're like, yeah.
What was your name?
Um, Pallumi.
Pallumi.
It's Pallumi Shogas, Bumbo.
No, that's okay. I just wanted to .
Yeah, because the official name is like just follow me, but because of like passports and IDs, you need to like have the food.
I think I saw your email actually, so okay, all right, okay.
So then I'll still reply to your email, okay, but see, in one week I'll be able to give you an extension,
and see if you can figure out a way to get a computer.
Again, you don't need something powerful, because what I can do is I can give you then access to chameleon cloud,
you can do development there.
For the next assignment?
For the next assignment, yeah.
And for this one, we need a lot of resources.
So you're saying, for the next assignment,
I can do it on the cloud?
I can access it into the cloud?
Yeah.
So I just need something temporarily to do it.
Something to be able to connect.
And then I think if you're saying the second one is cloud,
I think I can use the labs.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Thank you so much, sir.
All right, keep me posted, okay?
Yes, sir.
Hey, Professor?
Yes.
So I just took the quiz, and I was pretty sure that I got everything right,
but apparently I got half of them wrong.
Is there a way to see the answers to the quiz after I took it?
Not immediately after, so I usually release the answers two days after the deadline.
Okay.
For Queens 2, you'll be able to see the answers next Wednesday at midnight in one minute.
All right.
Cool.
Thank you.
Yep.
And then if you do have further questions, just send me an email and I'll clarify.
If maybe the answer was wrong, I can clarify if it was wrong or not.
Okay?
Okay.
Thank you.
Yep.
We'll see you next time.
What was your name?
Dylan.
Just activate your account.
Perfect.
So see if you can set up the password.
Yes.
Mine also expired.
What is your name?
Surya.
Surya Dejan.
So, Surya Teja Nulu, right?
Yes.
I just activated it right now.
Let's see if you can set up your passport and two-factor authentication, okay?
Do it in the next couple of days so that it doesn't impact.
OK?
Thank you.
I'm going to close the zoom meeting okay
Will I receive an email from New React?
No, no, I think you can use the old emails, but it should work now.
You shouldn't say that your account is deactivating.
I'm actually seeing myself, because it's the first year that I'm using this platform, because
discontinued the GitHub Classrooms that someone was using, so now see if you can see the old
email where I asked you to set up your account.
Yeah, that one is right here.
There's my access.
Sign me.
Oh, account was created for me, set up password.
There we go.
Oh.
Do you see?
An email it says your password token reset has expired.
Yeah, reset.
Do the reset.
No.
So far, no email.
Actually, there might be another link in the original email
to request another token.
Oh, let's see.
I saw some students being able to figure it out and not understand.
This link is valid for you.
That's where you could request an audio wallet right here.
You can put in your school email address if you not put it at all.
Yeah that's my school email address.
Now I'm not writing that.
We will see.
It takes a little bit of time because the server is actually sending an email to a proxy
I saw that there is a little bit of a delay sometimes.
Makes sense.
And that's why you know when you cloned the Refile Story,
you have to use the jump post as well.
Yeah.
I guess the pain.
It is a pain in use of the jump.
My whole systems one class that I took here
was all through the jump server.
And we had to do all of our assignments through the servers here at DePaul.
He wanted us to do all of our assignments through a text editor.
No IDE.
Is that Michael?
Yeah.
Yeah, that's Michael for you.
Yeah, but I mean, it was, especially for people that never used the Terminal or Bash in Linux.
Great introduction, though.
Have you used it before yet?
Yes, I did.
Luckily, I have.
Because when Microsoft ended support for Windows 7, I was like, I'm not going to do it.
Oh really? So that's what motivated me?
And that was the first moment of me to install Ubuntu on my laptop.
I was like this is actually really nice. Why is there not more software running on Linux?
And then over the years, of course more software to become supported.
Since Windows 7, that's like...
Yeah, I think it was 2017 or 2018.
Yeah, something like that. Wow.
That's how long I've been using Linux.
I'm curious about this because there's always students that know how to use this stuff.
How do you learn this?
I mean, I did the same.
So actually, for me, we had a class, which I'm thinking about introducing it at DePaul as well.
It was called Introduction to the Utilization of Operating Systems.
So it's not intro to OS, but it's how to use OS.
But they will teach you how to use it in minutes.
So command line, bash, scripting, you know, that kind of stuff, configurations, you know,
just, you know, common things between multiple distributions, you know.
So then after that, there was no way back.
I was like, wow, I think we're one of these teams.
So cool.
I think what took me the longest was the file structure.
It took me the longest figure.
I was like, where is my home folder?
Where is this program I installed?
Yeah.
That was taken the longest.
But after learning it, it's this phenomenal tool.
And of course, a lot of software, a lot of systems
run on Linux.
So.
Yeah, yeah.
See, you know, what are you doing?
What did he call me?
Here's the reset instruction.
Oh, I'll click the wrong one.
It wants to be the one below it, reset password.
There we go.
Sure.
Let's see.
I'm going to take a look.
Here we go.
There we go, reset it.
Let's see if I can log in.
Yeah, normally I've been using IntelliJ for my IDE.
And I just found out, to use remote, you gotta pay what kinda? Ridiculous.
So now I'm going back to the future.
Do you have to pay for the remote? You have to pay?
Yeah to use remote in IntelliJ, you gotta pay.
It's not part of the free trial, or the free version.
No, the community edition.
Yeah you have to use the unlimited subscription to use remote access.
No way you can do that.
Yes.
No, it's not true.
I know, so
Sorry for my language break.
No it's all mess.
Wow.
I just looked it up and I was like, you gotta be kidding me.
Trying to see if you can get uh because you're a student,
if you can get like the education out.
Yeah it makes a lot of sense. I didn't even think about that.
You put your default e-mail there and I think they give you for like a year or two.
Okay.
It'll be enough you know and you'll get access to the ultimate.
Oh wow.
Yeah, I couldn't find it.
Because normally I was using uh virtual studio code,
or virtual studio code but the last uh three quarters
I was going with professors that recommended IntelliJ, so I was using that for a while.
It's good, you know, it's a powerful IDE, but unfortunately we have the development
stuff.
Yeah.
That's a lot of ways.
I don't understand some of these decisions, but, you know.
Just to get more money from you.
Yeah.
See if you can hear the educational.
Otherwise, I mean, for now,
VS Code seems to be...
Yeah, this seems like the way to go.
Anyways, if it happens that VS Code will do the same thing one day,
we'll go back to VM.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, and luckily I know how to do that now.
Plus, you can put more plugins nowadays, you know.
Yeah.
And thanks to Mike, I know how to do everything through a text editor.
Yeah, perfect.
Yeah.
Well, good luck, okay?
Yep, thank you.
I'll let you know if you have any questions.
Explaining, Dave.
Yep.
Yeah.
Thank you.
so
I'm going to get a little better.
Thank you.
All right.
So, let's try it.
so
Alright, let's see.
I don't know.
What the heck?
Thank you.
I didn't want to get any of them in one place.
Last.
I'm going to stop here.
Thank you.
I'm not going to be the first one.
I can't see that.
I won't see that.
I won't understand what he's done.
and I'll be able to see them on YouTube.
And I'll be able to see them on YouTube.
And that's all.
And I'm not going to take a break until I talk.
I'm just talking to you.
I need to go with them.
I'm talking to you.
I've got a question.
I'm going to go ahead and go,
and I'll be able to see you on YouTube.
And I'm going to go ahead and put it in your list.
And then I'll be able to do that.
the
yeah
okay
So, we'll do it.
Okay, so the English was looking at the middle of the house.
The second one?
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Yes, I can.
I'll call.
Thank you.
.
Let's pray.
Thank you.
.
Amen.
you
So, let's move forward.
Thank you.